<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reasons taken out of Gods Word and the best humane testimonies prouing a necessitie of reforming our churches in England Framed and applied to 4. assertions wherein the foresaid purpose is contained. The 4. assertions are set downe in the page next following.</title>
            <author>Jacob, Henry, 1563-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 194 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 46 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14338</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S120955</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856146</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856146</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21672</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21672)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 993:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reasons taken out of Gods Word and the best humane testimonies prouing a necessitie of reforming our churches in England Framed and applied to 4. assertions wherein the foresaid purpose is contained. The 4. assertions are set downe in the page next following.</title>
                  <author>Jacob, Henry, 1563-1624.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 83, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Schilders],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Middelburg :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Henry Iacob.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Controversial literature --  Puritan authors --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Congregationalism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21672:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21672:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>REASONS TAKEN OVT OF GODS WORD AND THE BEST HVMANE TESTIMONIES PROVING A NE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CESSITIE OF REFORMING OVR CHVRCHES IN ENGLAND. Framed and applied to 4. Aſſertions wherein the foreſaid purpoſe is contained. The 4. Aſſertions are ſet downe in the Page next following.</p>
            <q>
               <p>I beleeved, therefore I haue ſpoken.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 116.10.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>One thing is neceſſarie.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Luc. 10.42.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="outline">
            <pb facs="tcp:21672:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The 4. Aſſertions.</head>
            <list>
               <label>Pag. 1.</label>
               <item>1. It is neceſſarie to reforme the Churches of England, their Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisterie, and Ceremonies.</item>
               <label>Pag. 57.</label>
               <item>2. For the ſpace of 200. yeares after Christ the Viſible Churches vſing governement were not Dioceſan Churches,but parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ordinary Congregations only: and the Biſhops (as they were peculiarly called after the Apostles) were only Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall not Dioceſan Biſhops, differing from other Pastors only in Prioritie of order not in Maioritie of rule.</item>
               <label>Pag. 67.</label>
               <item>3. The Scriptures of the New Testaments do co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine &amp; ſet forth vnto vs (beſides the government by Extraordinary Offices, Apostles Prophetes Evangelistes) an ordinary forme of Church-governement vſed then.</item>
               <label>Pag. 70.</label>
               <item>4. The ordinary forme of Church-governement ſet forth vnto vs in the New Testament, ought neceſſarily to be kept ſtill by vs; it is not changeable by men, and therefore it only is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:21672:2"/>
            <head>To the high and mightie Prince IAMES by the grace of God King of England, Scotland, France, and Ireland, <hi>Defender of the faith, &amp;c. Grace and peace be multiplied in Christ our Saviour.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight high, mightie, and gracious Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, in moſt humble wiſe your Maieſties loyall &amp; devoted Subiects who for the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of our ſoules deſire the Reformatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our Churches according to Gods word, do caſt downe our ſelves in the true affection of our heartes before your Royall preſence, whom we acknowledge to be the nobleſt pillar of the Goſpell and the greateſt hope for the propagation and eſtabliſhing thereof that is in all Chriſtendom. Beſeeching your Highnes to extend your Kingly ayde and furtherance vnto vs in our foreſaid moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie and iuſt deſire, with protection alſo toward our innocen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies againſt the Oppreſſion of our Adverſaries in this cauſe. Their Oppreſſions of vs are and have ben many, very grievous. and of long continuance. For the which we<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> have knowen that your Maieſtie formerly hath ben touched with a godly &amp; tender com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration towards vs. As it is with all humble thankfulnes ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged (to your immortall honor) by * a Reverend Father,<note place="margin">M. Cartwe. Epiſt. to the King be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil. on Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</note> one that heeretofore taſted therof, and now lately ſleepeth in the Lord. The truth of God maintayned then, is the very ſame which we now dutifully ſeeke for. Our conſciences are rather more certified of the goodnes and neceſſitie of theſe Ordinances of God, by how much more tyme we have ſpent ſince in examining and trying the Reaſons alleaged to and fro about the ſame. The great increaſing alſo of Papiſtes and Libertines among vs ſince this time, aſſureth vs that the preſent Eccleſiaſticall Orders are
<pb facs="tcp:21672:3"/>more friendly to them then to the ſynceritie of the Goſpell. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, the moſt lamentable diſſentions and diverſitie of opinions in matters of Religion breaking foorth every where among the people (contrary to lovely Vnitie, which the Dioceſan Biſhops do vainly pretend to be a proper fruit of their Office, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that which other Churches refuſing them and their Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions do ſweetly inioy) this animateth vs with all dutifull in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſeeke this Reformation aforeſaid ſo divinely co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vnto vs. Laſtly, we have had it from your Maieſtie very oft, that whatſoever things in our Churches we can ſhew to be <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary</hi> to Gods word, ſhalbe by your gracious meanes removed: and whatſoever (yet out of vſe with vs) may appeare by Gods word to be Neceſſary; ſhall be eſtabliſhed. May it pleaſe your moſt gracious Majeſtie, let this word ſtand. We crave, we deſire nothing more. And leſſe then this how can we deſire? I hope it is ſhewed and declared competently in the Treatiſe following that the matters in queſtion wherewith our conſciences are trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, are in very truth Contrary to Gods Word. And heere we moſt humbly beſeech your Majeſtie on our bended knees to think of vs no otherwiſe. The Lord is witnes to our ſoules, we by not; that of meere conſcience to God we ſeeke the right, and refuſe the wrong, namely theſe Humane Traditions Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call: and not (as our Adverſaries ſuggeſt) of any contentious or peeviſh mind. There is no other reaſon in the world moving vs in this matter, but becauſe we ſee it with our eyes that all ſuch things are directly Contrary to Gods word; and that Chriſtes owne Ordinances which yet we want are neceſſary to be enjoyed for our ſoules health. They are vaine words of men vnadviſed, yea of corrupt mindes, and ſtudying to flatter, which ceaſe not to inculcat (and ſpecially in greateſt preſence) that theſe thinges are Indifferent, and arbitrary. I pray God it com not to paſſe by ſuch reaſoning, that many will hold all things indifferent like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe: indifferent of what Religion they be: indifferent whether of any, or of no Religion. Which conceits I feare already are entered in to the hearts of many, yea of thouſands in England. But we beleeve (and the truth is) Gods word never knew any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differency in matters of the Church or of Religion: wherein all
<pb facs="tcp:21672:3"/>things (whether great or ſmall) have ever ben either ſimply good or evill, neceſſarie or vnlawfull. Our Adverſaries do ſharply riſe vp againſt vs, and labour to charge vs with moſt odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous reproches and accuſations, chiefly laid out to your Majeſtie and others neere you. Where as they know well, that we com nothing ſhort of themſelves touching any duty to your Highnes Crowne and Dignitie. And in affection to your perſon we haue ben before them all, yea then when it hath gon the harder with vs for it. Only in a point of Religion we differ from them, that we beleeve Gods written Word ought to be our ſole warrant for all things Eccleſiaſticall, and even ſo namely for thoſe with vs now in controverſie, if at all they be lawfull. Which point they vtterly deny. And for this cauſe they cry out importunatly that we are <hi>Schiſmatikes.</hi> There is no end of their ſpeeches and writings loading vs with this extreame injurie. Wherevnto though we haue to long vſed more then patient ſilence, yet all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes we can not do ſo.<note place="margin">Ierom. ad Pammach.</note> We are taught by a worthy ſaying of an ancient Divine; <hi>Jn crimine Haereſeos neminem oportet eſſe pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientem.</hi> When any is accuſed of Haereſie or Schiſme, (as we are) he ought by no meanes to put it vp in ſilence, but to make his lawfull defenſe, Wherefore I thought it needfull (being, though the meaneſt of my brethren, yet by Gods grace one of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants in the Miniſtery of the Goſpell, and being not only in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, but alſo<note n="“" place="margin">Anſwer to the hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring Reſ. &amp;c.</note> in particular thus traduced by them) needfull therefore I thought it to be to giue out ſom Reaſons of our faith and conſcience in this cauſe. Whereby our innocencie &amp; ſound judgment heerein (through Gods bleſſing) ſhalbe made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, and our Adverſaries chiefeſt evaſions being taken away the truth and neceſſity of this Reformation is more diſtinctly and cleerely demonſtrated. I deny not (moſt noble Prince) but that there be divers Brethren deſiring this Reformation, who yet affirme not all that I affirme in this Treatiſe, or ſomething not ſo fully. Neither are the Dioceſan Biſhops, nor their fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, all wholy of one mind. Yet touching vs, I know we wholy agree in the grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of our deſire; which is the Sufficiency and perfection of Gods word in whatſoever matters meerely Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall. I ſay, meerely Eccleſiaſticall. For in matters any
<pb facs="tcp:21672:4"/>way Civil no man doubteth but God hath left liberty vnto mans judgment and liking. Howbeit not ſo in things meerely Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall; as after ſhall further be ſhewed, God willing. And thus every ſober minded man well conſidering the Reaſons heereaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter deduced from this ground, will (I hope) in ſhort time not hardly accord with vs.</p>
            <p>But now it remayneth (Gracious Soveraigne) that I intreate your Majeſtie, which in moſt lowly and humble maner I do, to pardon my boldnes. Firſt in gathering theſe Reaſons, &amp; to ſuch a purpoſe as heere is ſignified. Secondly in preſenting them to your Highnes. Thirdly in preſuming heerein to alleage and cite ſome of your owne goulden ſentences. Your religious wiſedom eaſilie perceaveth that this purpoſe, beſide mine owne due de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence; concerneth a moſt waightie and holy work: viz. the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of many and great diſorders (as we are perſwaded) in our Churches, which hitherto haue ben the proper cauſes of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakeable hinderance to the Goſpell, and of calamitie to infinit faithfull lovers thereof among vs. In which regard how glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a worke this will be and how acceptable to God, how hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable for your ſelfe, and how neceſſary for vs, your Highnes (I am ſure) right well vnderſtandeth; and I hope by viewing theſe ſmall labours of mine you may ſomwhat more vnderſtand. My deſire was to be brief and plaine in ſo important a cauſe. Wherefore I haue touched the pith of all in a few, namely in 4. Aſſertions for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with ſhort and cleere proofes. And to whom ought I chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to offer them but to your Highnes? Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidering that you have willed vs to <hi>preaſe by patience and well grounded Reaſons to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade all the rest to like of our iudgements,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In Baſilicon Doron, to the Reader.</note> 
               <hi>or where we ſee better grounds on the other part to incline therevnto.</hi> Which by Gods grace we ſhalbe ready alwayes to performe. Conſidering alſo that yours is the Soveraign power heere to give generall redreſſe to theſe our not only temporall, but alſo ſpirituall grievances in our conſciences. And conſidering that you not only know, but alſo embrace and profeſſe moſt religiouſly the ſame maine Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of our faith and ground of this perſwaſion of our Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences which we reſt vpon: viz. <hi>The holy Scriptures abſolut per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in matters Eccleſiasticall.</hi> Laſtly, conſidering how you have eſtabliſhed the Churches in your Maieſties other Kingdom
<pb facs="tcp:21672:4"/>of Scotland, and in your Ilandes of Ierſey and Guernſey, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly already. Therefore have I ben bolde in all duty to offer theſe Reaſons to your Maieſtie, as to one whom they principally concerne. Where alſo we do all beſeech you to ſuffer theſe words of exhortation. Be ſtrong in the Lord, and looſe not the things which you have don. Yea proceed, and do this noble work a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong vs alſo. The Lorde is with you, while you be with him. When you follow cloſe his wayes, your very enemies ſhalbe at peace with you. It ſhalbe eaſie to do it. To your people gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally it wilbe moſt acceptable, as a thing looked for before: to all neighbour Proteſtant Countreys ioyfull, as wherein we ſhalbe all neerer linked togeather. To be ſhort, every way it ſhall bring more Honor and leſſe inconvenience to your eſtate, then perhaps you may ſuppoſe. Finally, Gracious Soveraigne, as tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching my preſumption in medling with your writings and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying them to this purpoſe, I can ſay nothing, but only ſubmit my ſelfe to your wiſe, vertuous, and religious conſideration. Sure I am, when we your loyall and faithfull Subiects did firſt ſee and read the ſame, it was the greateſt ioy and comfort to our heartes that could come vnto vs. And therfore I could not but give ſom notice thereof, alwayes in the moſt dutifull &amp; obedient affection of my heart that I can expreſſe. The Lord Ieſus in mercy bleſſe your Maieſtie for euer, &amp; preſerve your precious ſoule from flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery and falſhood. AMEN.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maieſties humble, obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and faithfull Subiect <hi>HENRY IACOB,</hi> a Miniſter of Gods word.</signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>Colimus Imperatorem vt hominem à Deo ſecundum, &amp; ſolo Deo minorem.</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Tertull. ad Scapul.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="assertion">
            <pb facs="tcp:21672:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21672:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>The 1. Aſſertion.</hi> It is neceſſarie to reforme the Churches of England, their Ministerie, and Ceremonies.</head>
            <argument>
               <head>A generall Argument.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Ll things <hi>Contrarie</hi> to Gods word ought of neceſſitie to be reformed.</p>
               <p>But with vs in England there are Formes of ſome reputed viſible Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, viz. vſing Church-government, their proper Miniſteries or Offices, and alſo divers Ceremonies <hi>Contrarie</hi> to Gods word.</p>
               <p>Therefore with vs in England it is neceſſarie to reforme the Churches, their Miniſterie, and Ceremonies.</p>
            </argument>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Aſſumption is proved in 8. Reaſons.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, we haue the 2. Commandement in the Deca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue;<note n="*" place="margin">Exod. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not make to thy ſelfe any image or likenes of any thing, &amp;c. Thou ſhalt not bow downe to it nor worſhip it.</hi> Which is a perpetuall and vniverſall Law now ſtill for all Chriſtians, to the ſame very effect and purpoſe alſo, as it was heeretofore vnto the Iewes. Where we muſt note, that God forbiddeth not the ſame Idoll-worſhip heere, which is forbidden properly in the 1. Commandement, where he ſaith;<note n="“" place="margin">verſ. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not haue any other Gods before me.</hi> This heere forbidden is an other kind of idolatrie. In the firſt he forbiddeth whatſoever Divine or Godly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor given vnto any thing beſide vnto God himſelfe. But<note n="*" place="margin">verſ. 4.5.</note> heere he forbiddeth all Meanes being <hi>Humane Inve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tions,</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:21672:6"/>whereby men would giue honor to the true God. And namely all Outward meanes; which we call Gods<note n="*" place="margin">Externus Dei Cultus; Liturgia.</note> Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Worſhip or Service. Yet conſider alwayes that in this Commandeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſuch Outward meanes of honoring God are not denyed to mens diſcretio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as are Civill, either meerely or mixtly. But only ſuch are heere denyed as are meerely Eccleſiaſticall things, and ſerue ſimply to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Religion. As all Eccleſiaſticall <hi>Rites, Actions, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries, &amp; Formes of Viſible Churches;</hi> which being (as it were) ſenſible images ſerving ſimply for religious or Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call vſes, and being meerely the inventions of men, muſt needs by this Commandement be all ſimply vnlawfull. Or, in Gods Outward worſhip this Commandement gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth leave to mens diſcretion &amp; wiſedom only touching meere Circumſtances, which are nothing els but Occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall or Accidentall things therein. And theſe Occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Circumſtances or Accidents are alwayes ſuch Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars, as whoſe Generalls are either Civill, or Naturall, or Written in the word. I ſay, theſe Particulars only (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding this Commandement) are permitted to men to appoint, or to change againe, at their diſcretion. In this text then there are 3. points to be noted.
<list>
                     <item>1. The matter.</item>
                     <item>2. The Author.</item>
                     <item>3. The reſpect due from vs vnto the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heere contained.</item>
                  </list>
The matter is the whole ſpirituall Meanes of worſhipping the true God. And namely the Outward ſpirituall meanes; that is, Gods Viſible Church, his Miniſtery, his whole Outward Worſhip and Service. 2. The Author of all this is preciſely determined, viz. God himſelfe, and no Man. 3. Such Inventions of men muſt haue from Gods people no reverence: but Gods owne ordinances muſt. And thus this 2. Commandement is truly vnderſtood.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:21672:6"/>
               <p>To this effect likewiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re many other places of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, excellent expoſitions and interpretations of this maine Commaundement. As,<note n="“" place="margin">Deu. 12 32</note> 
                  <hi>Whatſoever I commaund you, take heed that you do it: thou ſhalt put nothing thereto, nor take ought therefrom.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Iſa. 30.21</note> 
                  <hi>This is the way, walke ye in it: turne not to the right hande nor to the left.</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Pſal. 19.7</note> 
                  <hi>The Law of the Lord is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</hi>
                  <note n="§" place="margin">Pſal. 119.113.</note> 
                  <hi>I hate vaine inventions, but thy lawe doe I love.</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Nomb. 15.39.</note> 
                  <hi>Yee ſhall have fringes, that when ye looke vpon them, ye may remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber all the commandements of the Lord, and do them: and that yee ſeeke not after your owne heart, nor after your owne eyes, after the which ye go a whoring</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Matt. 15.13.</note> 
                  <hi>Every plant that my heavenly fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath not planted, ſhalbe rooted vp.</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">2. Tim. 3.16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>The whole Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, making the man of God perfect vnto every good worke.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Ioh. 16.13</note> 
                  <hi>The holy Ghost ſhall lead you into all trueth.</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Gal. 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>No ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adde to any thing to a mans Testament:</hi> much leſſe may we adde vnto Chriſtes Teſtament. Which is only the holy Scriptures of the Apoſtles, and nothing els in the world. Laſtly,<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 16.17.18.</note> 
                  <hi>Marke them which make ſchiſmes and offenſes</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Gal. 1.8. 1. Cor. 3.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Beſides the doctrine which you haue learned and avoid them. For ſuch ſeruenot the Lord Ieſus Christ, &amp;c.</hi> With ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other mo places to the ſame purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Out of all which this doctrine remaineth cleare and firme, that all <hi>Humane inventions,</hi> or <hi>Vnwritten Traditions Eccleſiasticall</hi> are directly contrarie to Gods woord. Yea being but <hi>Beſide</hi> the Scripture, they are flatly <hi>contrarie</hi> to it in theſe places. And therfore Gods owne word (which is only the holy Scriptures as was before noted) ought to be religiouſlie beleeved, and held to be for vs as a moſt perfect and abſolute demonſtration of all things whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever being properlie and ſimplie Eccleſiaſticall or religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. Which was the ſpeciall end and vſe they were given for. As likew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſe they were given vnto the Iewes; even to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:21672:7"/>be ſo abſolute and perfect for them, ever ſince God did give them any holy Scripture. From which groundes &amp; principall places of Gods wor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e thus declared, we will now conclude and frame our firſt Reaſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">
                     <label type="milestone">
                        <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon </seg>1</label> IF we have Dioceſan and Provinciall Churches vſing governement,&amp; Miniſteries or Offices proper to them, and alſo Ceremonies (that is, Rites) now in controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, all which are Inventions &amp; Traditions vtterly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Scripture;<note place="margin">Vnwritten Traditions.</note> then we have ſome reputed Churches as touching their outward viſible forme, and miniſteries, and Ceremonies, contrarie to Gods worde.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">But we haue Dioceſan &amp; Provinciall Churches vſing government, their proper Offices, viz. the Provinciall &amp; Dioceſan<note n="*" place="margin">viz. as they inflict Eccle<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Cenſures.</note> high Commiſſion, Provinciall and Dioceſan Ruling Biſhops, alſo controverted Ceremonies which are all Eccleſiaſtical vnwritten Traditions, no wayes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in, but cleane <hi>beſide</hi> the Scripture.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore they are <hi>contrarie</hi> to theſe places of Gods word, they are ſimply evill, &amp; of neceſitie the other, viz. the <hi>Pariſh Churches</hi> in England ought to bee reformed, freed, and cleered of them all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where it is firſt to be noted, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Note </seg>1</label> that al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thoſe forenamed matters Eccleſiaſticall, or any other els, which may or can be lawfull, are and ought to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in the Scripture, either expreſlie or by neceſſarie conſequence. Other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we affirme they are meerely Humane Inventions &amp; Traditions, contrarie to the Scripture.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Note </seg>II</label> 
                  <note place="margin">Reputed Viſible Churches of divers kindes.</note> Againe it is to be noted, that in the eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imation of men a Viſible Church (that is, which is indued with power of Spirituall outward governement) is of di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ers formes and natures. Nevertheles in trueth and in ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie deed Chriſt hath ordeined for vs only one kinde of a Viſible Church
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:21672:7"/>in his worde. And this only ought to be allowed and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved to be a true Church by all Chriſtians. For who is it, that can or ever could make any ſocietie of people to be a Viſible Church, but Chriſt onely? <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Some men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme the Vniverſal nomber of profeſſed Chriſtians in the world to be one viſible Church, calling it the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> or Vniverſal viſible Church. And the <hi>Catholikes</hi> taking holde hereof, do conclude that likewiſe there is &amp; ought to be one Catholike and vniverſall governement Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall vnto which all other Churches and their govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments muſt be ſubordinate. But in Gods worde there is no ſuch viſible Church nor governement anie where to be found. This is meerly deviſed by the witte and will of men. Againe men eſteeme a whole Nation profeſſing the Goſpell, to be one viſible Church,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> and they call it a <hi>National</hi> church. Likewiſe a Province a <hi>Provincial</hi> church: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> and a Dioceſe a <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Church. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> But none of theſe like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe can be found in the whole new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Chriſt.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Only a <hi>Particular ordinary constant Congregation</hi> of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in Chriſtes Teſtament is appointed and reckoned to be a viſible Church.<note place="margin">Particular &amp; Pariſhio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches are the onely true Viſible Churches.</note> And therefore ſo ſtandeth the caſe now heere with vs in England alſo, and ſo we ought to eſteeme it. The which that it may more clearelie ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be true, I have thought good to ſett downe this brief Table following, wherein all the divers and ſundrie ſenſes of a <hi>Church</hi> in the<note n="*" place="margin">We ſpeak not of the Iewes chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Law, which wee knowe was Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall &amp; only one in the world vnder one High Prieſt. Which were Figures and are ceaſed. Such alſo was that One Church in the wildernes, Acts 7.38 which was yet nevertheles but one particular Aſſembly a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>o in one plate gathered to geather ſo neere as ſuch a multitude could be, Exod 19 11 &amp;c.</note> New Teſtament are plainlie &amp; diſtinctlie ſhewed. And yet none of the 4. forenamed vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Churches (as ſome do repute them) are any where there to be found.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21672:8"/>
               <list>
                  <head>A Table briefly ſhewing all the divers and ſundry ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations in the New Teſtament of this word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly we tranſlate a Church. Wherein we may eaſily ſee which is the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e true and proper viſible Church of Chriſt to which the goverment Eccleſiaſticall of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>fe doeth alwayes of right app<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rtaine.</head>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Eccleſia</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is taken.</label> Ciuilly and originally for a<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 19.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.39.40.</note> particular Aſſembly of Citizens in one certaine publike place about matters of the Common wealth.</item>
                  <item>
                     <label>
                        <hi>Eccleſia</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is taken.</label> Religlouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie for a Church
<list>
                        <item>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly
<list>
                              <item>in the next and neereſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion aunſwering to the Originall ciuill vſe thereof. This is a Particular Viſible Ordinary Congregation of Chriſtians meeting for reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious &amp; Eccleſiaſticall acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons &amp; exerciſes. And this is the only true Viſible Church of Chriſt hauing from him the Spirituall power of or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der &amp; gouernment in it ſelfe ordinarily. The proper Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters thereof are the onely true ordinarie Miniſters of Chriſt. This we read of in the Scripture in 2. reſpects:
<list>
                                    <item>Definitly; This is ſome certaine known<note n="“" place="margin">Mat. 18.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap> Revel. 21. Col. 4.16. Gal. 1.2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>. Theſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>.14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>. Cor. 16.1, 19. 2. Cor 8.1. Rom. 16.4.16</note> parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation in ſome certaine particu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lar place which we may go vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to conſult with and obey.</item>
                                    <item>Indefinitlie; where is vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood This, or That, or<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>. &amp;c. 1. Cor. 12.11. Mat. 6 33. Iſa. 2.1.2, 3. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>. Pet. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>.5.</note> any other particular ordinary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                              <item>in a proportion more remote or further of. Such is the Inuiſible or Intelllgible Church ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutly Catholike: that is the number of<note n="†" place="margin">Ephe. 3.10, 15, 21. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>.27.</note> all Gods Elect both in Heauen and in Earth.</item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                        <item>Figurati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uely by a
<list>
                              <item>Metaphore; Such is a holy &amp; well ordered Chriſtian<note n="“" place="margin">Rom. 16.5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>. Cor. 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                       <desc>••</desc>
                                    </gap>.</note> familie reſembling as it were a very Church though in deed it bee but a part of a true and proper Church.</item>
                              <item>Synec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doche viz. of the
<list>
                                    <item>Viſibilitie, when the Church it ſelf that is the whole cannot but only ſome parts of it may be Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible or Senſible at any time to any one man that needeth the vſe of it Such is the Catholike Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant Church, w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> is<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 16.18. 1. Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                             <desc>•</desc>
                                          </gap>2.28.</note> properly an Inuiſible &amp; Intelligible Church as it is conſidered wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>ly togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that is, as it is one Church.</item>
                                    <item>Societie; as when only the<note n="“" place="margin">Act. 15.4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                                             <desc>••</desc>
                                          </gap>.</note> Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of a particular Congregation (hauing Miniſters, yet without and beſide their Miniſters) are called the Church.</item>
                                 </list>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:21672:8"/>
               <p>Whereby it is evident that no <hi>Catholike,</hi> or <hi>Vniverſall</hi> Church Viſible is any where in all Chriſtes New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to bee found: and therefore in no wiſe is ſuch a Church to be allowed. Neither yet any <hi>Nationall,</hi> or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinciall,</hi> or <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Church. Only a particular ordinarie <hi>Congregation</hi> is heere found (and ſo is to be held) properly and only a true viſible Church of Chriſt.</p>
               <p>Moreover heereby it appeareth, and it is likewiſe to be noted,<note place="margin">Note III.</note> that the nature and office of a <hi>Biſhop</hi> alſo is not of one maner, but of divers. It is as the former word <hi>Church</hi> very ambiguous, and muſt be likewiſe neceſſarily diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed.<note place="margin">Biſhops of ſix ſortes.</note> Six ſortes of Biſhops have ben and are known in the world.<note n="1" place="margin">1.</note> A Pariſhionall Biſhop, who is a Paſtor of one ordinary Congregation only. Such are all the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes mentioned any where in the New Teſtament, and alſo in writers within the ſpace of 200. yeares after Chriſt.<note n="2" place="margin">2.</note> A Dioceſan Titular Biſhop, who was Biſhop of a Dioceſe in title and in name only, in Eccleſiaſticall governement having no more power then any other co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Paſtor. He differed not in any eſſentiall part of the ordinary Paſtorall Office, but was only Preſident or Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derator co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly (yet by his fellow Paſtors free conſent) over the Paſtors of a Dioceſe. Such perhaps firſt of all was<note n="“" place="margin">Ann. 190</note> 
                  <hi>Iulianus</hi> the tenth Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria.</hi> In whoſe time firſt<note n="*" place="margin">Euſeb. 5.9.</note> mention is made that there were divers Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in that Citie, and he Biſhop of them. The firſt ſorte of theſe Biſhops we wholy allow. The ſecond we do not ſimply deny. They were not much vnlike to the Biſhops now lately appointed in Scotland.<note n="3" place="margin">3.</note> There is a Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan ruling Biſhop. He had more power then any of the reſt of the ordinarie Paſtors (though yet not any ſole power) to rule in his Dioceſe. It may be this began at
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:21672:9"/>
                  <hi>Alexandria</hi> with<note n="“" place="margin">Ann. 260.</note> 
                  <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the thirteenth Biſhop of that place: which ſeemeth to be <hi>Ieroms</hi> meaning, where he<note n="*" place="margin">Ierom ad Evagr.</note> ſaith, that ſome prioritie in Biſhops continued there <hi>from Marke to Heraclas and Dionyſius.</hi> At <hi>Heraclas</hi> (it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable) was a period of one ſort, and with <hi>Dionyſius</hi> began another.<note place="margin">Prioritie of Order
<list>
                        <item>1. Pari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</item>
                        <item>2. Dioceſan.</item>
                        <item>3. Maioritie of rule Dioceſan.</item>
                     </list>
                  </note> Prioritie of order in one Biſhop over a Pariſh (that is one particular compleat Congregation) ſeemeth to haue continued excluſively from <hi>Marke</hi> vnto <hi>Iulianus:</hi> over a Dioceſe from <hi>Iulianus</hi> to <hi>Heraclas</hi> incluſively: and then Maioritie of ruling in the Dioceſe to haue begun with <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the next Succeſſor after. Nothing letteth vs but that thus we may probably thinke: Seeing thus <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Ieroms</hi> relation ſhall well agree. How ſoever it was, this is certaine, that neither the one nor the other was knowne before theſe times heere expreſſed.<note n="4" place="margin">4.</note> A Dioceſan Lord Biſhop was he, who ruled ordinarilie in his Dioceſe by his ſole power. This grew vp from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer by litle and litle. But it ſeemeth not to haue ben eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed in Ambroſe, Ierome, &amp; Auguſtines time: though ſoone after (we doubt not) it tooke place over the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.<note n="5" place="margin">5.</note> A Patriarchall Biſhop: and they were firſt 4. in number,<note place="margin">Of which kinde the Archbiſhop may be rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned alſo.</note> viz. at <hi>Rome, Antioch,</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Or els Cae ſarea. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil. Nic. 1. Can. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieruſalem, Alexandria.</hi> They began by mens voluntarie regarding the Biſhops of thoſe principall Cities aboue other, ſometime before the Nicene Councell. But they were by an ordinance eſtabliſhed firſt in that Councell. Howbeit yet they were not Lords over the Churches, till a long while after. In the firſt Councell of <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> an other Patriarch was eſtabliſhed at Conſtantinople.<note n="6" place="margin">6.</note> A Catholike or Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall Biſhop<note n="*" place="margin">Bonifacius was the firſt</note> began at <hi>Rome,</hi> about 600. yeares after Chriſt. Who alſo hath had his growinges and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, and was not perfect Antichriſt, till ſome ages after.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:21672:9"/>Now all theſe latter, that is, the 3.4.5. &amp; 6. ſort, are at leaſt <hi>Beſides</hi> the Scriptures: yea they are cleane <hi>Contrarie</hi> to the firſt, which hath place and allowance in the Scripture. And therefore theſe are plainlie <hi>contrary</hi> to Gods word, &amp; vtterlie vnlawfull. Wherefore alſo the<note n="“" place="margin">As name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie that in D. Bilſons perpet. go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment, pag. 260.</note> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon accompts and Catalogues of the ſucceſſion of Biſhops from the Apoſtles times to our dayes are very deceiptfull and falſe. When as al theſe are called by one name indifferently <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops</hi> without diſtinction, yet their Offices are exceeding divers and no way like. Yea theſe later directlie contrarie to the firſt, as hath ben ſaid.</p>
               <p>Againſt this it is<note n="*" place="margin">D. Bilſon in perpetu. govern pa. 299.300. in effect</note> obiected, that <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were properly <hi>Dioceſan ruling Biſhops.</hi> Yea ſuch as wee call Lord <hi>Biſhops,</hi> that is, vſing<note n="*" place="margin">pag 232.</note> ſole authoritie: and had charge of mo particular Churches then one. Which is to be in deed a Dioceſan Biſhop. But they and their Offices are founde in the<note n="“" place="margin">1 Tim. 3. and 5. Tit. 1.5. &amp; Tit. 3.</note> Scripture: viz. To ordeine Paſtors in divers Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and to cenſure them, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I anſwere, the very <hi>Apostles</hi> did not<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 14.23. &amp; 1.15, 23. &amp;c. 6.3 5, 6. &amp; 1 Ti. 4.14. w Act. 16.2.</note> make Miniſters nor Cenſure by their ſole and ſingle Authoritie, but ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more in the preſence and with ſome liking of that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church whom it concerned. Therefore much leſſe did <hi>Timothie</hi> or <hi>Titus</hi> ſuch matters ſolely and ſingly, who were lower then Apoſtles. And therefore they were no Lord Miniſters certainelie. Further it is vntrue, they were no proper <hi>Biſhops</hi> at all: neither Dioceſan, nor any other. For all proper Biſhoppes were<note n="“" place="margin">D. Bilſon pag. 227. &amp; 232.</note> 
                  <hi>affixed</hi> to certaine places and certaine charges where they were to ſerve and<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 20.38 1 Pet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 2. Theodoret. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n Ephe. 4.</note> attend (in purpoſe) continually. But <hi>Timothie</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> were never <hi>affixed</hi> to one certaine charge. For they (like the Apoſtles) intended not a conſtant continuance in a place, but after a time of their aboade in one Nation, tranſlated both their
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:21672:10"/>preſence and their labours into another Countrie. Being <hi>Comites Apostolorum,</hi> Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panions or Aſſiſtants to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,<note n="“" place="margin">See Bez. Annotat. in Acts 19. &amp; de Mini. grad. cap. 5.</note> indued doubtles with the extraordinarie gift of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers tongues, and therefore did goe (being co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monlie ſent or called by the Apoſtles) hither &amp; hither, to the end that they might perfect ſuch Churches as the Apoſtles had planted, but not throughlie furniſhed. And this is evident by the text. Firſt <hi>Timothie</hi> was choſen and ordayned at<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Lystra,</hi> went into Phrygia, Galatia, Myſia, Troas: being at Philippi was ſent to<note n="“" place="margin">1 Cor. 4.17.</note> Corinth, from<note n="*" place="margin">1 Theſ. 3.1.2, 6.</note> Athens went to Theſſalonica: from<note n="§" place="margin">Act. 19.22</note> Epheſus went to Macedonia: after he was left at<note n="“" place="margin">1 Tim 1.3</note> Epheſus againe to order &amp; redreſſe things there. And yet<note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.9.1.</note> thence he was ſent for away and depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. A litle before Paules death he was at<note n="“" place="margin">Phil. 1 1.</note> Rome, &amp; from<note n="*" place="margin">Phil. 2.19 23.</note> thence to goe to the Philippians. Wherefore <hi>Timothie</hi> was no ordinarie proper Biſhop of any ſort, nor affixed to anie certaine place, but a verie <hi>Evangelist</hi> (as alſo the<note n="*" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.5.</note> Scripture calleth him) that is, an vnlimited, extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porarie function in the Churches. The like was <hi>Titus.</hi> Paule choſe him for his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>panion &amp; helper, and had him<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 2.2.</note> with him to Ieruſalem. Alſo he ſent him to<note n="§" place="margin">2 Cor. 8, 17.</note> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth. Hee left him in<note n="“" place="margin">Tit. 1.5.</note> Crete a while: but ſends for him the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce<note n="*" place="margin">Tit. 3.12</note> away anon after to Nicopolis. A litle before Pauls death he was with him at<note n="“" place="margin">2 Tim. 4.10.</note> Rome, &amp; from thence he went into Dalmatia. Both theſe therefore were verie <hi>Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelistes,</hi> and no maner of ordinarie Biſhops. Neither in deede were there anie Dioceſan Biſhops, or Dioceſan Churches, that can be found in all the New Teſtament.</p>
               <p>Then they will obiect, that ſome things are <hi>Indifferent</hi> in Eccleſiaſticall actions; and doubtles ſo are certaine Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, &amp;c. It is not neceſſarie that theſe ſhould bee warranted particularly in the Scripture.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:21672:10"/>
               <p>I anſwer; The Papiſts do hold their Eccleſiaſticall Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions or Rites to be meerelie indifferent in their nature, and to be neceſſarie onelie as the Church commaundeth them. This is manifeſt by D. <hi>Stapleton</hi> ſaying:<note n="*" place="margin">Staplet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Promtuar. Catholic. part. Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drageſimal. pag. 99.</note> 
                  <hi>Omnes vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in corum [Rituum Eccleſiasticorum] vſu nullam neceſsita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem poni, ſed liberè aſſumi vel non aſſumi: modò abſit contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptus, qui non in Ceremoniam ſed in Eccleſiae prepoſitos, qui cam instituerunt, imò in Christum cadit, dicente ad illos Christo, Qui vos ſpernit me ſpernit.</hi> Alſo by the <hi>Rhemes Testament,</hi> ſaying:<note n="“" place="margin">Rhem. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſtame. An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notat. in Math. 15.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Neither fleſh nor fiſh of it ſelfe doth defile, but the breach of the Churches precept defileth.</hi> Likewiſe writeth <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in his diſcourſe of their Church-Ceremonies. But yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding every good Chriſtian knoweth well, that their Traditions are plainly ſuperſtitious and vnlawfull. How then ſhall not ours alſo be the like? What are ours better then theirs? Further, though <hi>Circumstances</hi> be indifferent and may be chaunged by men, yet <hi>Formes of Churches</hi> are not ſo; nor the <hi>Church Ministeries,</hi> nor <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> nor (in a word) any <hi>Traditions Eccleſiasticall,</hi> whereof our former Reaſon wholy intreateth. We denie not then but that in Eccleſiaſticall actions the meere Circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces are in ſome ſort indifferent, that is, not neceſſarie to be determined by Scripture. But theſe truely are not to be called Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Traditions. Wherefore we muſt know that there is a great difference betweene <hi>Traditions</hi> &amp; <hi>Circumstances.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides Gods Ordinances ſpecified in Scripture, there are 2. other kindes of lawfull thinges in the adminiſtration of Church matters.
<list>
                     <item>1. Naturall Neceſſities.</item>
                     <item>2. Proper and meere Circumſtances.</item>
                  </list>
Naturall Neceſſities, are <hi>Perſons, Times, Places, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">what things only are in different. Circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</note> Proper &amp; meere Circumſtances (which onely are indifferent in Church actions) are Accidentall things wherof there is no neceſſitie, but either may or may
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:21672:11"/>not be vſed. They are of 2. ſortes, either <hi>Civill</hi> or <hi>Occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall.</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The <hi>Civill</hi> Circumſtances are ſuch as though they be vſed in Church actions,<note place="margin">To this do belonge all thinges of Comlineſſe and Dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cy.</note> yet even there they import only and meerely a Civill vſe. Which we ſhall eaſilie diſcerne thus: viz. when the ſame things in the ſame maner are vſed alſo in actions meerely Civill at other times and places. Such were Chriſtes<note n="“" place="margin">John 13. w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 1. Tim. 5.10.</note> 
                  <hi>Waſhing</hi> the Diſciples feet, the<note n="“" place="margin">Rom. 16.16.</note> 
                  <hi>Love feasts,</hi> &amp;<note n="*" place="margin">Iud. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Kiſsings</hi> in the Church meetings of old. The ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner at this day of the French <hi>Preaching covered. To come to the Church</hi> in this or that decent and comely <hi>common appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell.</hi> A commodious &amp; diſtinct <hi>Houſe</hi> for Gods Service, &amp;c. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
                  <hi>Occaſionall</hi> Circumſtances are ſuch particulars as ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial occaſion requireth and moveth vs vnto, namely when the Generall things are either vſuall in Civill cuſtome, or by Gods owne ordinance in Nature, or in the Word writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. As <hi>ſuch</hi> or <hi>ſuch</hi> Places, Times, Perſons, Things. Name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie to come together in <hi>Synagogues,</hi> or <hi>Temples.</hi> To vſe <hi>Pues,</hi> or <hi>Pulpits, &amp;c.</hi> To Pray <hi>Kneeling,</hi> or <hi>Prostrate.</hi> To eate and drinke at the L. Table <hi>leaning,</hi> or <hi>ſitting, &amp;c.</hi> In the<note n="“" place="margin">Mat. 26. 1 Cor. 11.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning,</hi> or at<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 20.7</note> 
                  <hi>Midnight.</hi> To Baptize in<note n="“" place="margin">Acts 16.15.</note> 
                  <hi>Rivers.</hi> Alſo the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles vſing of ſome<note n="*" place="margin">Gal. 3.24 &amp; 4.9.</note> Iewiſh Ceremonies among the <hi>vnconverted Iewes</hi> a while after Chriſtes death. Their<note n="“" place="margin">Acts 6.3, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 6.</note> let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the people to <hi>nominate</hi> their Miniſters. Churches <hi>more or leſſe</hi> populous, &amp;c. Theſe and ſuch like wee doubt not, are in Eccleſiaſticall actions in ſome ſorte <hi>Indifferent.</hi> I meane they are changeable, and either can not or ought not to be perpetuall: neither need they to be determined in Scripture. Although yet in their vſe they are not to be reckoned ſo indifferent, but that they ought neceſſarily to be ruled by the generall rules of Diſcretion and Charitie. Namely that in all of them Comelineſſe, Edification, the Avoyding of offence, and Gods glorie may be reſpected.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:21672:11"/>Thus then let it be noted, that we affirme in Eccleſiaſticall actions no other thing at all beſide theſe is or can be anie way indifferent by any meanes.<note place="margin">None of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> things in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>troverſie are indifferent; neither are they proper Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces.</note> But touching our forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Eccleſiaſticall vnwritte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Traditions (whether Formes of Viſible Churches, Miniſteries, or Ceremonies) they are of no ſuch nature, as thoſe things beforenamed either Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall neceſſities, or proper Circumſtances are. They are no way like to any ſort of them. Wherefore though Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances be indifferent, yet mens Traditions in Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can not be. Neither did theſe thinges ſtande otherwiſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Iewes vnder the Law. So that it remaineth ſure, that all Church-Traditions without Gods word (&amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all invented formes of Viſible Churches vſing go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement, offices of Miniſterie, and Ceremonies) are ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie evill and vnlawfull; and therefore of neceſſitie ought to be reformed.</p>
               <p>Yet ſome will reply and ſay, If men may inſtitute Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples or places meerely Eccleſiaſticall, why not alſo Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments meerely Eccleſiaſticall, &amp;c.?</p>
               <p>Touching Temples I aunſwere: They are eſteemed meerely Eccleſiaſticall or Religious places, becauſe things meerely Eccleſiaſticall or Religious are done in them. Howbeit the trueth is, their proper and principall vſe is partlie Naturall and partlie Civill. It is neceſſarie in Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for Church-Aſſemblies to bee in a place. It is Civill (namelie when peace &amp; proſperitie is) to have a commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious a comely and a diſtinct Houſe for the publike exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes of Gods worſhip. Which very thing is in Civilitie no leſſe requiſite for the publike grave actions of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Wealth alſo. So that at the moſt, a Temple appointed by men can not truelie be accoumpted a thing meerely, but mixtly Eccleſiaſticall. And ſo this Humane inſtitution we acknowledge is lawfull even for Religious affaires, when
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:21672:12"/>there is no further vſe therof at all. That is, if it be not held as Religious meerely, nor in the proper and principall vſe thereof. As the <hi>Surplice</hi> is with vs. It is an Eccleſiaſticall Rite:<note place="margin">So are likewiſe the Kneeling, Croſsing, Churching, Burying, &amp;c.</note> which the Temple can not be. It is meerely &amp; ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply Eccleſiaſticall. There is no reſpect had to Civilitie in it: conſidering that it ſerveth never in any Civill buſineſſe nor place, but it is onely in and for the Church &amp; Church actions. Much leſſe is there for it any Naturall neceſſitie. Beſide, the Preface of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-prayer-booke maketh it to have (with the reſt of the Ceremonies) <hi>a ſpeciall ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi> in Gods worſhip. Even as the Papiſts do alſo vſe it; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom immediatly we have receaved the ſame. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doubtles ſuch preſcript garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts meerly Eccleſiaſtical being Humane Inventions, are ſimply vnlawfull: although Temples for Gods Service be not ſo. Moreover we have to anſwere to this and ſuch like matters obiected to vs, in this wiſe.<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Cor. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>3. &amp; 14.23. &amp; 5.4. Math. 18.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</note> Such * places of Scripture as doe commaund Church-Aſſemblies and the publike Worſhip of God, the ſame do alſo by neceſſarie conſequence (in time of peace) commaund ſome commodious and diſtinct Houſes for them. But no Scripture by any neceſſarie conſequence commaundeth any diſtinct and meere Eccleſiaſticall Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at any ſeaſon. Therefore theſe things can not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared nor likened togeather. They are not both things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different alike. Nay, the one is by Gods word neceſſarie, the other vnlawfull.</p>
               <p>Some think that the appointing of the <hi>Altar</hi> in<note n="*" place="margin">Ioſh. 22.</note> Ioſhua, of the Feaſt of<note n="“" place="margin">Heſt 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Purim,</hi> and Davids ordayning<note n="*" place="margin">1 Chron. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>5.1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Singers &amp; Muſicians</hi> in the Temple, do prove that all religious mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters invented and inſtituted by men, are not vnlawfull.</p>
               <p>I anſwere, Howſoever they who appointed and ſett vp that <hi>Altar</hi> in Ioſhua might have deviſed ſome other thing
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:21672:12"/>leſſe ſcandalous then the forme of an Altar, whiche yet might as well have ſerved to the vſe they made it for, as the Altar did or could doe. Nevertheles this Altar was truelie no more but a civill monument or Signe, as being vſed no way in any Eccleſiaſticall or Religious action of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping God, but ſet vp as a ſpectacle only in the open fields or by the river ſide, though it ſerved for a token that the 2. Tribes and a halfe had a part with the reſt of Iſraell, and in the worſhip of their God. Not vnlike it might be to this; if the States of the low Countries ſhould commaund eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie inhabitant (being no Anabaptiſt) in that Countrey to weare a litle Dagger on their garmentes, to ſhew that they beleeve Magiſtracie and the vſe of weapons to be lawfull. Or as perhappes the Signe of the Croſſe was vſed by the Ancient Chriſtians dwelling amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g Heathens, to let them ſee they were not aſhamed of Chriſt crucified. All theſe are cleerely Civill, and therefore (wee acknowledge) in mens power it is ro ordayne or abrogate them. As for the Feaſt of <hi>Purim,</hi> that appeareth no where in the text to have bene a Religious Feaſt or Holy day. But onely a day of Civill vſe alſo: viz. of reioycing, of making merry, of ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding preſentes to friends, and giftes to the poore. As may appeare Heſt. 9.22. Yet if any contende that it was a Holy day for ſolemne Thankes-giving &amp; worſhipping of God in memorie of the rare deliverance of the Iewes from <hi>Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> malice: Though this appeare not, yet wee may an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, neither can anie man diſprove it, that <hi>Mordecai</hi> the Iewe (the<note n="*" place="margin">ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Authour of this inſtitution) was a Prophet of God, and Authour alſo of this booke of Heſter. So that then he ordained this conſtant Holy-day, not by humane diſcretion, but by Divine authoritie. Even as <hi>David</hi> did inſtitute the ſinging. Levites with Inſtrumentes of Muſike
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:21672:13"/>in the Temple. The<note n="*" place="margin">2. Chron. 29.25.</note> text (as it were of purpoſe) meeting with this obiection, importeth that <hi>David</hi> neither did nor might do theſe things by his Kinglie power, nor by anie diſcretion Humane, but only by Propheticall authoritie through Gods own commaundement. Where it is to be noted, that by vrging Gods abſolute &amp; all ſufficient Lawe for matters Eccleſiaſticall, wee do not reſtraine nor binde God, but only vs Men from adding of any thing in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Gods worſhip beſides that which hee him ſelfe hath inſtituted and ſealed vp in his Teſtament.</p>
               <p>It will be againe replied, This is true in deed, God hath given vs in his word this ſufficiencie for all Eccleſiaſticall or Religious matters neceſſarie to ſalvation: but not for all Eccleſiaſticall matters what ſoever.</p>
               <p>This is a frivolous exception, and moſt falſe. For firſt, divers of our preſent matters controverted are neceſſaric enough. They can not be thus reiected as thinges not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie: viz. the onely true Forme and Conſtitution of Chriſts Viſible Churches, with their due Miniſteries pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portioned to them. According to Gods ordinarie diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of grace by his worde, there is even Neceſſitie to enioy theſe (Gods own) Ordinances, and to bee free from all Traditions of men, eſpecially ſuch as are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trarie to his. Touching other things, which ſeeme ſinaller and of leſſe importance, as ſome eſteeme the Rites &amp; Ceremonies to be in Gods worſhip. I anſwere: our Argument before laid downe generally includeth all meere Eccleſiaſtical or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious things. I ſay, All. And where All is included, No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing is excepted. Wherefore we ſtill affirme and profeſſe that all lawfull Eccleſiaſticall Rites whatſoever are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained now in the Scriptures of the New Teſtament, and not onely thinges ſimply neceſſarie to ſalvation. Beſides
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:21672:13"/>that we muſt not forget how the wilfull maintayning of ſmall thinges amiſſe becommeth a great and haynous ſinne, wherevnto is due a fearfull puniſhment. As may be ſeene in him who<note n="*" place="margin">Num. 15.30, and 32.</note> with a high hande did but gather a few ſtickes on the Sabbath day.</p>
               <p>Nothwithſtanding all this, yet it ſemeth to many that theſe externall things Eccleſiaſtical are not matters of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, nor of Faith, &amp;c. And therefore may bee lawfull, though they be not contayned in the Scripture. I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, They are all truly &amp; properly matters of Doctrine, of Faith, and of Religion, appertayning to the
<list>
                     <item>1. Table &amp;</item>
                     <item>2. Commaundement in the Decalogue, &amp; to many other places of Scripture, as before hath bene ſhewed.</item>
                  </list>
It is the error of men not knowing the holy Scriptures proper and full vſe, or true extent, when any do thinke ſuch Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall things as theſe heere controverted are not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tained in the Scripture, &amp; yet that they may be lawfull. They are all ſimply vnlawfull, if they bee not contained in the holy Scripture. Wherefore, even all theſe things both the lawful &amp; vnlawfull, contained in the Scripture or not contained (Formes of viſible Churches vſing Government, Miniſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, &amp; Rites) are matters of Doctrine, of Faith, of Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, viz. true or falſe. So that the one ought as our life to be imbraced, the other as the very wayes of death to be avoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, eſpecially when we diſcerne and ſee them thus to be.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſon 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">EVERY Viſible Church of Chriſt (truly and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly ſo called) ought by Gods<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 18 17.</note> expreſſe word to have and vſe the Eccleſiaſticall government of it ſelf.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>very particular Congregation of Chriſtians is a" Viſible Church of Chriſt truly and properly.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The true Churches and the falſe.</note>"</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:21672:14"/>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore every particular Congregation of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans by Gods expreſſe word ought to have and vſe the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall governement of it ſelfe: viz. according to the order ſet downe for a Viſible Church in Gods word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſo in England conſequentlie the things that are directlie contrarie therevnto (<hi>Dioceſan</hi> and <hi>Provinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> Churches vſing government, with their Miniſters, &amp;c.) are directlie <hi>contrarie</hi> to Gods word, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ought of neceſſitie to be reformed.</p>
               <p>Heere firſt lett it be noted,<note place="margin">A Viſible Church.</note> that we vnderſtande a Viſible Church of Chriſt to be <hi>a Societie of Christians whiche any member may and must (on occaſion) have a viſible or ſenſible vſe of intirely and wholy togeather, the ſame having the power of Eccle ſiasticall governement in and for it ſelfe immediatlie from Christ.</hi> I ſay, The Church intirelie and wholie togeather may and muſt be vſed on occaſion. Conſidering that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this there is no text of Scripture in all the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, nor anie force of reaſon appearing.</p>
               <p>Then let vs alſo obſerve and marke theſe 3. pointes.<note place="margin">Note.</note> For proofe of our <hi>Aſſumption</hi> laſt before. 1.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The Viſible Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of Chriſt were in number<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 11.16. &amp; 4 17. &amp;c.</note> many &amp; divers (and not onely one) by the ordinance of God him ſelſe. So that it is falſe whiche is<note n="“" place="margin">Hooker lib 3. Sect. 1. pa. 132.</note> held that there is a Vniverſall Viſible Church like the Sea; which being but one properly, is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed and called by divers names according to the Countries and places by which it cometh. Nay, the Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Churches of Chriſt were by the Apoſtles ordination many in number, &amp; actuallie divided Bodies or Societies: The Sea properly and alwayes being but one Continued Body, was and is diſtinguiſhed meerelie by divers names. The Vniverſall Inviſible Church was and is in deed one in number: but I have ſhewed there were many<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in nom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:21672:14"/>of the true and proper Viſible Churches. Againe, the Iewiſh Viſible Church according to the Law, was in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber only one properlie vnder one High Prieſt, and having one Temple only at <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> But Chriſt and his Apoſtles changed that forme, and did inſtitute and leave the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches properlie in number many and divers, as I ſaide.</p>
               <p>Secondly they inſtituted and left particular ordinarie or conſtant Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregations true and proper Viſible Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: Or,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> they left not anie one Viſible Church (in the whole world) conſtitute and compact of divers ordinarie and conſtant Congregations. Both theſe points are moſt manifeſt and vndeniable in theſe places of holy Scripture following. Firſt that floriſhing and plentifull Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> was<note n="*" place="margin">1. Cor. 14.23.</note> but one particular Congregation. Whereof the Apoſtle ſaith thus, <hi>When the whole Church is come togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>into one place.</hi> Which alſo we may likewiſe affirme of the Church of<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 14.27.</note> 
                  <hi>Antioch,</hi> and of<note n="♣" place="margin">Iuſti. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr Apo. 2</note> 
                  <hi>Rome,</hi> and of<note n="“" place="margin">Act. 15.22, 25.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and of<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 20.28</note> 
                  <hi>Epheſus,</hi> &amp;c. in thoſe dayes. For though theſe Cities were great and populous, yet being vnbeleeving &amp; hatefull enemies to the Goſpell, each of them had then of faithfull Chriſtians but one particular conſtant Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation onely. Like as the Proteſtants are in the Cities at this day vnder the Spaniſh King; or as they were in divers Cities of France before the peace was made, &amp; as we were heere in London in Queene Maries time. Where yet we denie not, that then ſome particular Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregations being (as that of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 4.4</note> before) greater then other ſom, did by reaſon of perſecution meet occaſionallie and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainlie in divers<note n="♣" place="margin">Act. 12.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> ſmaller numbers. But theſe ſmaller numbers were not ſo many <hi>Churches</hi> properlie, becauſe they were vncertaine and occaſionall. A true and proper
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:21672:15"/>Church being alwayes neceſſarilie an ordinarie ſett com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panie and a conſtant ſocietie. Thoſe therefore notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding made but one<note n="“" place="margin">Act. 6.2.</note> particular &amp; compleat Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation or proper Church, which in time of peace (chieflie they growing yet more populous) were to be diſtributed and divided into ſundrie proper and ordinarie Churches, each of them a competent Congregation. Which we do obſerve further neere the end of our handling the 2. Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion afterward. Moreover, likely alſo it is in theſe cruell perſecuting Cities that ſo great a multitude of Chriſtians did not long keepe togeather, but many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie diſperſe and ſcatter them ſelves abroad into other quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Countries, whereby the whole number there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſmaller, as we may ſee they did at<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 8.1.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of <hi>Stevens</hi> perſecution, &amp;c. immediatlie after the great and ſuddaine increaſe of the Church there. All which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conſidered, it is plaine yet ſtill that in the greateſt Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or whereſoever els, the Apoſtles appointed and left true and proper Viſible Churches particular conſtant Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations. Which further alfo appeareth by thoſe many and diſtinct Churches of<note n="a" place="margin">Gal. 1.2. 1. Cor. 16.1</note> 
                  <hi>Galatia,</hi> of<note n="b" place="margin">2 Cor. 8.1 19, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Macedonia,</hi> of<note n="c" place="margin">1 Cor. 16.19.</note> 
                  <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> of<note n="d" place="margin">2. Cor. 8.24</note> 
                  <hi>Achaia,</hi> of<note n="e" place="margin">1. Th. 2.14 Gal. 1.21.</note> 
                  <hi>Iudea,</hi> of<note n="f" place="margin">Act. 9.31.</note> 
                  <hi>Galile</hi> &amp; <hi>Samaria,</hi> of<note n="g" place="margin">Act. 15.41</note> 
                  <hi>Syria</hi> &amp; <hi>Cilicia,</hi> of<note n="h" place="margin">Act. 14.23</note> 
                  <hi>Lycaonia</hi> &amp; <hi>Piſidia.</hi> Likewiſe by thoſe many Churches of the<note n="i" place="margin">Rom. 16.4</note> Gentiles, and the Churches of the<note n="k" place="margin">1 cor. 14 33</note> Saints, the Churches of<note n="l" place="margin">1 Cor 11.16</note> God, the Churches of<note n="m" place="margin">Ro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. 16.16</note> Chriſt, and<note n="n" place="margin">2. Cor. 8.18. &amp; 11.28 1. Cor. 4.17 Reve. 2.23. Act. 16.5 1 Cor. 14.34 3. Ioh. 6. Rev. 22.16.</note> All Churches. All theſe in number were (not onlie one, but) manie proper diſtinct Churches. Each of them being ſeverallie but one particular conſtant Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation. Wherevnto moſt fitlie agreeth that iniunction and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of our Saviour Chriſt touching a Viſible Church where he inſtituteth the externall ſpirituall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er thereof, ſaying,<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 18.17</note> 
                  <hi>Tell the Church</hi> or Congregation: <hi>If he
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:21672:15"/>heare not the Church, let him be vnto thee as an Heathen and a Publicane.</hi> Where he muſt neceſſarilie be vnderſtood of a particular Congregation. Which may be told and ſpoken vnto onely. As alſo that deſcription of a Viſible Church, which our publike Authoritie in England teacheth:<note n="“" place="margin">Artic. 19.</note> viz. <hi>A Viſible Church is a Congregation of faithfull people where the word of God is preached, and the Sacraments ministred, &amp;c.</hi> Doct. <hi>Bilſon</hi> alſo, where he ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">D. Bils. againſt the Seminaries. lib. 2. p. 170</note> 
                  <hi>The Church is never taken in the New or old Testament for the Priestes alone, but generallie for the whole Congregation of the faithfull. In Act.</hi> 20.28. <hi>The Church is taken for the People.</hi> And it is<note n="“" place="margin">Lib 3. Pa. 70.</note> 
                  <hi>Math.</hi> 18.17. <hi>The whole multitude of the faithfull where he and they</hi> (the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and the Offended) <hi>live.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 3.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> point here to be marked (ſerving alſo for proofe of our <hi>Propoſition</hi> before) is a generall and ſure <hi>Maxime</hi> in Divinitie: viz. The true and proper Viſible Churches of Chriſt both heeretofore, now, and heereafter, though manie in number, yet all are but one in nature, forme, and Conſtitution. And each of them hath ſimply one and the ſame ſpirituall or Eccleſiaſticall power immediatlie from Chriſt (not derived from any other) to governe it ſelfe withall. To which purpoſe the Scripture often ſpeaketh of the Viſible Church indefinitelie as of onelie<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 22.2, &amp;c. 1. Cor. 12.13. Mat. 6.33 1. Pet. 2.5. Iſa. 2.1, 2, 3. 1. Tim. 3.5.</note> one. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in Nature and Forme and in the true Conſtitution, as alſo in the ſpirituall power thereof, it is only one. Yea it ſaith alſo in plaine termes that there is<note n="“" place="margin">Ephe. 4.4. 1. Cor. 12.13</note> 
                  <hi>one Body:</hi> where is ment the Church. But it is to bee vnderſtood, that it is one in nature and power, as I ſaid. Which muſt of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie be ſo, becauſe Chriſtes<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 18.17.</note> Inſtitution of a viſible Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches externall ſpirituall governement before noted, muſt belong equally to every true and proper Viſible Church. Wherefore alſo the nature, forme, &amp; Conſtitution of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:21672:16"/>one muſt be the ſame that this is which heere Chriſt ſignifieth in <hi>Matthew.</hi> Which evidentlie was a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregation, as before wee obſerved. To which purpoſe alſo one of our Adverſaries<note n="*" place="margin">Hooker lib. 3 pag. 132.</note> a famous Schole-di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſheweth that by cleere and vndeniable reaſon the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement Eccleſiaſticall belongeth to everie Viſible Church properly ſo called. And the practiſe of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike Churches doeth iuſtifie and confirme it. Which being ordinarie particular Congregations, each of them did or might by their Miniſters (and them ſelves in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence conſenting)<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 14.23 2. Cor. 8.19</note> chooſe Elders and<note n="“" place="margin">1. Cor. 5.4, 5. Mat 18, 17.</note> excommunicate offenders. Neither certainly did Chriſt ever inſtitute or the Apoſtles practiſe divers kindes or formes of Viſible Churches. Neither let they any to have greater or leſſer ſpirituall power then other. But they appointed one forme and one power for the Churches (queſtionles) eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie where and alwayes. Therefore they all (though being many in number, yet) were and are one in nature, and forme, and power every-where and for ever.</p>
               <p>Whence now it followeth by a neceſſarie and vndenia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſequence that theſe 3. Concluſions inſuing are like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe certaine and true.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Every particular ordinarie Congregation of faithfull people in England<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</hi> By right from God.</note> is a true &amp; proper Viſible Church.</item>
                  <item>2. Everie ſuch Congregation heere and everie where is indued with power immediatly fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt to governe it ſelfe Eccleſiaſticallie or fpirituallie.</item>
                  <item>3. Everie true and proper Viſible Church everie where is but one ordinarie or conſtant Congregation only.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And then no one Church conſiſteth, neither can conſiſt of many ordinarie diſtinct Congregations. Wherfore no
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:21672:16"/>Dioceſan Chuch is ordained or allowed by Chriſt, no Provinciall, no Nationall, and ſo likewiſe no Vniverſall vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church with an externall governement correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the ſame, as the <hi>Catholikes</hi> heretically do holde.<note place="margin">A Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, an He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retike.</note> A Vniverſal Militant Church I deny not: but a Vniverſal or Catholike Viſible Church with correſpondent governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment I do deny, and ſo likewiſe the reſt. Now heere thus we do for this reaſon, becauſe it is not poſſible, if there be indeed one Vniverſall Church properly, or where there is a Nationall Church, or Provinciall, or Dioceſan, that there the particular ordinarie Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregations are or can be eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med ſo many true and proper Churches. Theſe can not ſtand togeather with any of the former. Everie of thoſe is directlie contrarie to theſe. Seeing theſe in ſuch caſe are properly but Members and partes of the other, and not in them ſelves proper and intier Churches. Which yet in the places of Scripture * before cited the H. Ghoſt doth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie affirme. Where if he ſpeake not properly, who doth?<note place="margin">Pag. 19.20.</note> Or what is in Divinitie a proper ſpeach, if the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuall phraſe of the H. Ghoſt in Scripture be not proper?<note place="margin">Note.</note> And ſurely to this point, if we marke it well, doth all our preſent Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie come; that is, to ſett downe What is a Viſible Church of Chriſt truly and properly. Seeing each true Viſible Church hath evermore from Chriſt power and right of governement in it ſelfe, as before is noted. Let this therefore be well declared what is a true Viſible Church, and we ſhall ſoone agree. We affirme that every particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ordinarie Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation is and ought to be allowed for ſuch a Church. And heerevpon do we ſtand. I am not ignorant of the common and vulgar phraſe of ſpeach a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men both ancient and of late, both vnlearned and learned, who have vſed to call everie of thoſe other a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:21672:17"/>Church (as a Dioceſan Church, a Provinciall, a National, and alſo a Vniverſall Church) meaning, it ſeemeth, that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie of theſe may be trulie and rightlie called a Viſible Church. But this is only the cuſtome of ſpeach among men. And<note n="*" place="margin">Mos trium literatum tyrannus. Bez. Annot. in Luc. 23.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Custome is a Tyrant,</hi> as a Reverend Father ſaith well. It is no warrant nor ground for any thing in Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The word of God alone muſt ſuffice vs heerein. Yea we conſider not what advantage we give the <hi>Heretike Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes</hi> againſt vs, by acknowledging a Catholike Viſible Church. It followeth from this neceſſarilie that there is &amp; ought to be on earth a Catholike or Vniverſall governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment Eccleſiaſticall. This is a Concluſion wherevnto M. <hi>Hooker</hi> ſetteth down expreſlie<note n="*" place="margin">Hook. 3. Sect 1.</note> both the Propoſition and Aſſumption: viz.
<q>
                     <p>Everie Viſible Church,<note place="margin">Pag. 132.</note> truly and properly ſo called, ought to have a correſpondent Eccleſiasticall governement.</p>
                     <p>But there is a Catholike or Vniverſal Viſible Church on earth.<note place="margin">Pag. 126. and 132.</note>
                     </p>
                  </q>
To which Premiſſes everie childe now can quicklie adde the Concluſion.</p>
               <p>Ergo, <hi>There is and ought to be on earth a Catholike or Vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall governement Eccle ſiasticall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And I am perſwaded, that this overſight or error among vs hath cauſed Thouſandes to turne Catholikes, that is members of Antichriſt and enemies to the true Churches and ſervants of Chriſt. For if there be properlie one Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church and governement Eccleſiaſticall throughout the world, then this muſt be in ſome one place eminently. For ſome whither we muſt go, when Chriſt biddeth vs <hi>Tell the Church.</hi> Now there is no place in all the world ſo likelie as Rome is to be the Viſible ſeat and ſpring-head of the Vniverſall governement of the Catholike Church, if in deed there be any. Therfore moſt eaſilie me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are drawen
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:21672:17"/>to be Roman Catholiks, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this is not denyed that there is a Catholike Viſible Church. Which ſelfe ſame advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage we give alſo to our Pontificall Hierarchie in England againſt the true eſtate and due governement of Chriſtes Viſible Churches heere. For while we grant them (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by error or by overſight) that there is &amp; may be truly and properly a Dioceſan Viſible Church, they will eaſilie conclude that then there may &amp; ought to be a correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Dioceſan governement. Which (as before I obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) overthroweth quite the proper being and governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of each particular or Pariſhionall Church. But we, becauſe Chriſt and his Apoſtles throughout all the New Teſtament have appointed &amp; every were allowed the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhionall Aſſemblies, as to be cleerely &amp; abſolutly diſtinct in themſelves, ſo to be Viſible Churches truly &amp; properly, and withall a correſpondent Eccleſiaſticall governement to be in each of them, as before hath bene ſhewed; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore heerevpon do we ſtand, this do we vrge that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Chriſt and the Apoſtles practize ought to be a rule for Chriſtian Churches, as every where, ſo heere in England: vpon this do our Conſciences reſt aſſuredlie. Becauſe (as before I ſaid) who is it that may preſume to ordaine any forme of a Church ſave Chriſt only? Eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie overthrowing that forme of a Church and governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which Chriſt hath ordeyned, as theſe Dioceſan and Provinciall Churches with their proper Miniſters do. <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae nomine armamini, &amp; contra Eccleſias dimicatis.</hi> You arme your ſelves with the name of the Church, and fight againſt the true Churches.</p>
               <p>In this place I can not forget how ſome thinking the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ves deepe Politicians, do imagin that they ſee our Grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds to be directlie againſt a Monarchie or Kingly State. For
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:21672:18"/>this Eccleſiaſticall governement being Popular (ſay they) it wil require the Civill governement alſo to becom con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed to it. Alſo they thinke it can never bee menaged without trouble and tumult.</p>
               <p>Firſt we abſolutelie denie that any manner of Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall Governement requireth the Civill Governement to becom conformed to it. This is a moſt falſe conceite. The bounds of either Governernement are diſtinct and cleerlie ſevered the one from the other: albeit each doth ayd &amp; ſuccour the other. But what ſhould I reaſon heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of? This their inſimulation is againſt none other then Chriſt him ſelfe and his bleſſed Word, wherein he hath inſtituted no other ſtate of a Church Viſible but a parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Congregation only. Shall we impugne and accuſe the true Church of Chriſt? Nay, ſhall we accuſe Chriſt him ſelfe and his Goſpell; that heerein he yeeldeth vs not the true, right, or beſt forme of a Church? And therefore we will of our owne heades deviſe and conſtitute a better. God forbid that any Chriſtians ſhould ſo do, and wilfully maintaine this doing alſo. But they think this maner of go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement will becom tumultuous and troubleſom in the State: and ſo it will proove hurtfull to the Prince. I would demaund, why thinke they that the Church government (as we deſire it) will be troubleſom &amp; tumultuous? They will anſwere, becauſe we require of neceſſitie that Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Miniſters, and Excommunications, &amp;c. muſt be <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular.</hi> Which can not but bring with them commonly tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mult and much trouble, if not confuſion and perill to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie. Wherevnto I replie, that this were verie true in deed (viz. much trouble and tumult would commonly follow, and perhaps perill to divers) if we deſired or ſought for popular Elections of <hi>Dioceſan Biſhops.</hi> Such as we read of &amp;
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:21672:18"/>finde to have ben vſed in many places vnder Chriſtian Princes from 300. yeres after Chriſt hitherward for a long time. As for example at <hi>Antioch, Alexandria, Rome, Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople, &amp;c.</hi> In theſe and other Cities verie great ſtirres, tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multes, and confuſions among the People have riſen in deed not ſeldom times, even in and about ſuch their Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. The Eccleſiaſticall Hiſtories are full of examples to this purpoſe. But ſuch running togeather of a whole Citie or Dioces, ſuch voice-giving of ſuch multitudes of people we deſire not: neither do we any wayes allow it. It was a corrupt remainder in deed of the Peoples auncient free voice-giving to the Election of their <hi>Pariſhionall Pastors or Biſhops.</hi> For ſuch all ordinarie <hi>Biſhops and Pastors</hi> were pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitively in the Apoſtles dayes, and ſuch every where they were left by them, as before we have ſhewed. Every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie <hi>Biſhop</hi> then (I ſay) was only of a <hi>Pariſh</hi> (as the Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents call it) that is of one particular Congregation only, and no greater. And ſo their <hi>Elections</hi> were accompliſhed by the free conſent and voyce-giving only of the <hi>People</hi> of each of theſe particular ordinarie Congregations, or Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes. Now it is true indeed, we acknowledge we allow and do deſire ſuch <hi>Elections and Excommunications</hi> by the People. Neither is this to bee reckoned anie <hi>Popularitie</hi> which can be either prejudicious to Princes, or tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in it ſelfe. No, it can not be an inconvenient order, but moſt reaſonable for any place or people in the world. Namely ſeeing we do expreſly hold this aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe (and we hartilie pray that it may bee noted) but as it is grounded on 4. Circumſtances.<note place="margin">Power Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances wheron the fitnes of the Peoples co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth</note> 
                  <note n="1" place="margin">1.</note> In regard that it is (as we are well aſſured) a Divine order and ordinance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted for each Church by Chriſt and his Apoſtles: the trueth whereof (we hope) hath evidently appeared in this
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:21672:19"/>
                  <note n="2" place="margin">2.</note> Reaſon laſt handled. Conſidering that we allow the <hi>Peoples</hi> conſent and voice-giving in <hi>Elections, Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, &amp;c.</hi> to be done only by the Chriſtian People of one <hi>Pariſh,</hi> that is, of one particular ordinarie Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion only, and by no greater nor larger number of People by any meanes, as before hath bene likewiſe ſhewed.<note n="3" place="margin">3.</note> Conſidering that in the maner heereof we hold this only to be neceſſarie &amp; ordinarie, that the Eccleſiaſticall Guides there (apart fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>People</hi>) do firſt by themſelves prepare and determine the whole matter, namely in ſuch ſort that the <hi>People</hi> may not neede to do ought afterward but only Conſent with them, and freelie ſignifie their conſent it it.<note n="4" place="margin">4.</note> If anie where it ſhould fall out that this <hi>People</hi> thus gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp; being ſo few, will yet preſume to be in their <hi>Church-Elections, &amp;c.</hi> vnrulie and violent, then the Princes next dwelling <hi>Officers of Iustice</hi> may and ought to make them keepe peace and quietnes. Which thing how eaſie it is for the meaneſt of them to do, the ſimpleſt may perceaue. All which verilie being well conſidered, this Eccleſiaſticall Governement queſtionles is moſt reaſonable, yea neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie. And it is childiſh, &amp; without all wit to cry out againſt vs (as our Adverſaries do) <hi>Popularitie, Anarchie, and Enmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to Princes,</hi> for this our ſo wel grounded and ſo approved an aſſertion.</p>
               <p>Another thing is heere to be well remembred, that <hi>M. Hooker</hi> and <hi>M. Tooker</hi> the noble Patrons of Pluralities and Nonreſidencie are vtterlie defeated in this their purpoſe. The former<note n="*" place="margin">Hook. lib. 5. ſect. vl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>im.</note> maketh this his Reaſon for them, becauſe it is a miſtaking (ſaieth he) to thinke that the particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations are by Gods ordinance ſo many diſtinct &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Churches. For (as he holdeth) there is but one Viſible Church properlie, and the ſame Vniverſall thorough the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:21672:19"/>whole world. As for particular Congregations they are not properlie ſo many Churches, neither diſtinguiſhed at all by God but only by men. And therefore everie Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter is a Miniſter properlie to the Whole Church; but by men according to diſcretion only is limited to this or that Congregation, there to have maintenance made ſure to him by Law, &amp; there to teach, till men ſee it fitt to imploy his giftes in another Benefice, or elſwhere. All which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are meerly Mens ordinances, by men they may be diſpoſed and diſpenſed with againe as to thoſe in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie ſeemeth good. And ſo both Pluralitie of Livings and Nonreſidencie from the ſame ſhalbe both lawfull and honeſt. This is the effect and drift of his reaſon. And even on the ſame foundation alſo buildeth <hi>D. Tooker.</hi> Yea only this ground he hath, and none other. Where nothing els needeth anſwere but this his aſſertion;<note n="*" place="margin">Fabrike of the Church, pag. 45.</note> 
                  <hi>Diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Pariſh Churches is of meere poſitive law, not of Divine.</hi> For my part, I would graunt this Reaſon to be in deed ſound and good for their purpoſe; (and not only for that, but alſo ſingular and moſt pregnant to ſet vp the Romane Papacie too) if this their Foundation were not manifeſtlie contrarie to Gods word. But before it hath ben ſhewed to be cleerer then the light that Diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Pariſhes in ſome ſort, that is, of particular Churches is by Gods own ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce in the Apoſtles Writings, and not by the meere poſitive law of men. Wherefore this is evident to be a moſt vngodly and ſhameles Defence pleading for, or excuſing that wretched ſinne of ſoule-murdering Nonreſidencie, as if it were a thing allowable and not ſimplie evill. It can not excuſe this ſinne to alleadge that Plurified men may haue their 2. Benefices neare togither; perhaps within halfe a myle, a myle, or 2. myle the one of the other. This will not helpe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:21672:20"/>them any more then a man can be excuſed, who taketh &amp; keepeth two wives at once: though yet by the one he be not drawen farre away from the other. Gods law diſallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that former no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this latter. Yea I avow, There have ben who haue kept two wives at once, honeſter men and more approved of God, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any Miniſter now in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland having 2. Churches or Charges lying howſoever. And yet I acknowledge, to have two wives at once, is ſimply againſt Gods worde.</p>
               <p>Well, yet this will not ſatisfie ſome: neither will they yeeld that every particular Congregation of Chriſtians ſhould be allowed for a diſtinct and a proper Church Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; and ſo to inioy their owne Eccleſiaſticall governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment within themſelves. Albeit againſt it they have no reaſon, vnles perhaps this only. If it were ſo (they will ſay) yet will not thereby all things becom perfect. Somewhat notwithſtanding will bee wanting or amiſſe oftentimes. How then ſhall this be holpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or amended? Not by Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, or Dioceſan Ruling, or Lord-Biſhops?</p>
               <p>I anſwer, Somewhat wilbe amiſſe alwayes in whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Eccleſiaſticall governement vpon earth. Nevertheles there is no need, nor good vſe of theſe, nor of anie Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall Vnwritten Traditions in Chriſtes Churches. We believe and know Gods Written word to bee ſufficient. Speciallie ſeeing theſe are ſo directlie contrarie to the only true forme and nature of Chriſts Viſible Churches in his word, as hath bene ſhewed. A greater Eccleſiaſticall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement then the Churches wee know none. There is nothing without the Church above it: viz. Eccleſiaſtical<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and ſpirituallie. Seeing each Church hath her power and governement (as before is declared) immediatly from Chriſt. Yet it is true (beſide the Magiſtrates honorable
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:21672:20"/>aſſiſtance) verie oft there is great, and ſingular, yea ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times in a ſorte neceſſarie helpe to bee had by Synodes. Which are meetings of choyſe men out of many Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: and theſe are leſſer or greater as occaſion requireth. Whoſe counſailles, adviſes, and determinations are moſt expedient and wholeſome alwayes. But touching any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Governeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t by Synodes, or neceſſarie impoſing of their Synodall Concluſions, Decrees, or Canons vppon Churches without their particular free conſentes, this ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to be a meere Humane ordinance. I can not finde it (either expreſlie, or by neceſſarie conſequence) in any part of Chriſtes Teſtament. Thus writeth heereof the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend <hi>M. Whitaker,</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Whitak. de Concil. pag. 44.</note> 
                  <hi>Quod omnes atttngit, ab omnibus approbari debet.</hi> That which concerneth all, ought to be approved of all. Againe,<note n="“" place="margin">Pag. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Concilia ſi ſimpliciter neceſſaria ſint, Christus ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubi precipiſset celebrari, aut cius ſaltem Apostoli. Quod tamen nuſquam ab illis factum eſſe legimus.</hi> If Councills were ſimply neceſſarie, Chriſt ſomewhere would have commaunded to keepe them, or at leaſt his Apoſtles. Which yet we read that they did no where. Further,<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>Etſires ipſae de quibus in Concilio deliberatur &amp; conſultatur, ſint ſacrae &amp; religioſae, tamen hoc ipſum Congregare Epiſcopos est merè</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Although the things deliberated and conſulted of in a Councell be holy &amp; religious, yet this thing to aſſemble Biſhops or Paſtors of divers Churches togeather, is meerelie Civill. I know well ſundrie godlie men do hold that Synodes have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to preſcribe and rule Eccleſiaſtically by Gods Law even ſundrie whole Churches though they ſeverallie conſent not. But with reverence to their names, I take it the trueth is otherwiſe. Only in the <hi>Actes</hi> wee finde ſomewhat that hath a kinde of likenes to ſuch Synodes. And it is but a kinde of likenes, or ſcarſe that: for it is farre from the ſame
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:21672:21"/>thing. Thus it is: <hi>In Act.</hi> 15.6.25. we find a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Apoſtles, with the reſt of the Church at Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem and with a few other ſent to them from the Church of Antioch. Where theſe do make Decrees and impoſe them on the Churches: yea on divers Churches which had<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 16.4.</note> not ſent any in their names thither. And on the Church of Antioch, who had perhaps but 4. or 5. there preſent. This ſheweth that this comming togeather at Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem was a verie Extraordinarie Synode, comparing it with our Synodes in vſe now, yea indeed nothing like to them. Firſt heere the<note n="“" place="margin">Act. 15.2</note> text ſaith, The Apoſtles onely and the Elders at Ieruſalem were ſought vnto. And it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that heerein the Apoſtles Extraordinarie office &amp; po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer tooke place: viz. by impoſing their Decrees on Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches who had no perſons, and on one Church, viz. of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch who had few for them there preſent. In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect they at Ieruſalem aſſume alſo aſpeciall authoritie of the H. Ghoſt, where they ſay,<note n="*" place="margin">vers. 28.</note> 
                  <hi>It ſeemed good to the H. Ghoſt, and to vs.</hi> Which no Aſſemblie of ordinarie perſons could or can aſſume to them in ſuch maner. Only where the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles were preſent and conſented, there they might. Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallie after this we never finde that any Churches vſed the meanes and power of Synodes till about <hi>Constantines</hi> time for almoſt 300. yeares ſpace. Which if it had ben an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce Divine for the Churches always, they neither ought nor ſurelie would ſo long have neglected the ſame. Seeing in that vvhile there vvere moſt waightie and continuall occaſions requiring this Divine helpe, if they had ſo eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it. Which ſeeing they did not, we may well thinke in thoſe firſt times they held it not to be ſo. Nevertheles Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodes (when they may be had) are for counſaill, adviſe, &amp; better reſolution co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually profitable &amp; moſt wholeſom,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:21672:21"/>as hath ben ſaid. And being well ordered, do make ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larlie for Vnitie. Whereby alſo each Churches ordinarie governement may be much holpen &amp; amended. And yet the ſame with power and authoritie ought to be held ſtill within it ſelfe only.</p>
               <p>Now touching our Synodes at this day in Englande, they may be excepted againſt iuſtlie in 3. reſpects. Firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they conſiſt principallie, if not only, of Provinciall &amp; Dioceſan L. Biſhops (whoſe Offices are heere ſhewed, to be plainlie contrarie to Gods word) and of ſuch other as are theirs. Alſo our Synodes power is not ſuperior, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior and ſubiect to the L. Biſhops will and liking: which is vtterlie againſt the nature of true Synodes, and the rule of Gods word. Laſtlie they impoſe Eccleſiaſticall Canons on the Churches which give no conſent vnto them: as if they had power from God over the Churches thus to do. All which before we have ſeene to be cleane contrarie.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſon 3.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To have no place nor part in anie Church.</note>THAT any (being a Chriſtian) ſhould have no place nor part at all in any true &amp; proper Viſible Church of Chriſt, is contrarie to Gods word. Speciallie that any ſuch ſo ſtanding ſhould Eccleſiaſticallie rule manie Churches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes"> But our Dioceſan Biſhops (profeſſed Chriſtians) have not any place nor part at all in any true and proper Viſible Church of Chriſt. And yet they rule Eccleſiaſtically, ſom 300. ſom 400. proper and diſtinct Viſible Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore they are all contrarie to Gods word, and ought neceſſarilie to be reformed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>The first part of the Aſſumption is thus proved.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">If a Dioceſan Biſhop with vs have any part at all in any
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:21672:22"/>true and proper Viſible Church, then he is Paſtor in ſom Church or one of the People.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">But one of the privat People he is not any where. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is he a right and true Paſtor ſuſtayning the charge of ſoules in any proper Viſible Church with vs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore a Dioceſan Biſhop with vs hath no part at all in any true Viſible Church.</p>
               <p>I am not ignorant that our Biſhops themſelves ſay that they are very Paſtors in all thoſe ſeveral Churches of their Dioces, and ſo are in a principall place, and have a chiefe part in them all. Which notwithſtanding is vtterly falſe, conſidering that they have ſom Hundreds of Churches in their Dioces which they never ſaw, nor by law are bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to ſee in all their lives. Are they then, or can they be true and right Paſtors vnto them? They can not be. It were a ſhame for any once to thinke that they might. Neither are they Paſtors to any one of the Churches vnder them more then they are to all. Therefore in deed they are true Paſtors to none of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor to any proper Viſible Church at all. Howbeit imagining and ſuppoſing them to be (as they ſay they are) Paſtors to thoſe Churches which are vnder them, then I reaſon againſt them and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude thus.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">If Dioceſan ruling Biſhops by the nature of their office are very Pluraliſtes and Nonreſident Paſtors,<note n="*" place="margin">Acts. 20.28. 1 Pet. 5.2. Prou. 27.18.23.</note> then they are plainly contrary to Gods word, and ought of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be cleane aboliſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">But Dioceſan Ruling Biſhops are very Pluraliſtes and Nonreſidents by the nature of their Office. Seeing everie particular Congregation is a true proper and intire Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church, as before hath ben ſhewed: and ſeeing they aſſume to them ſelves a Paſtorall charge of the Peoples ſoules in mo then one, yea very many ſuch ſeverall and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:21672:22"/>Viſible Churches in England, which they neither do nor can ſerve as Paſtors ought.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore they are plainly contrarie to Gods word, &amp;" ought of neceſſitie to be cleane diſſolved and aboliſhed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Or thus.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ſenſe or the light of Nature (beſides the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noted" ſcriptures) ſheweth that one proper Paſtor ſhould" have only one proper Viſible Church. For indeed</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.16. 2 Tim. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note>
                  <hi> who is ſufficient for that one?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">But a Dioceſan Ruling Biſhop hath not only one pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per viſible Church in his Charge. He hath 300. or 400. as before is ſaid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore a Dioceſan ruling Biſhop ſinneth againſt the" word, and alſo againſt the light of nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We denie not that one proper Viſible Church may poſſiblie have many Paſtors. But that One Paſtor ſhould have many proper Viſible Churches, is a thing ſenſeles, vnnaturall, and condemned both by God and man.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſon 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The true Paſtors of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice.</note>IT is the naturall and immutable off ice of a Paſtor both to Teach and to Governe (with the aſſiſtance of other Elders) his owne flocke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">But every Paſtor of each particular Church in England is truly and properly a Paſtor of the ſame Church where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is, and ſhall anſwer for the ſoules of his flocke which depend vpon him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore every Paſtor of each particular Church in England ought of neceſſitie not only to teach but alſo to governe his owne flocke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Touching the Propoſition, it is manifeſt to be the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural and immutable office of a Paſtor to governe his own
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:21672:23"/>flocke. Firſt ſeeing the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> which ſignifieth to do the office of a Paſtor, doth in the naturall propertie of it imply Governement and rule.<note n="*" place="margin">Rain, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer chap. 3. divi. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pag. 140.</note> As wee may ſee this word is vſed, <hi>Math. 2.6. Reve. 19.15. &amp; 2.27.</hi> And therefore even Civill Magiſtrates are called <hi>Rogne</hi> Paſtors, <hi>Ezek. 34.2</hi> and in <hi>Homer</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Paſtors of the people: in <hi>Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pides</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Rulers of chariots. Secondly the whole office of a Spirituall Paſtor is found in the Scripture to be both <hi>Teaching and Governing:</hi> as firſt this very word doth moſt plainly ſignifie <hi>Ioh. 21.16. Act. 20.18. and 1. Pet. 5.2.</hi> Alſo where the diſtinct parts of the Paſtors office are noted as <hi>1. Tim. 5.17.</hi> and <hi>1. Theſ. 5.12. Math. 18.17.18.</hi> Ad heervn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>D. Bilſons</hi> conſent with <hi>Athanaſius,</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Perp. gov. pag. 199.</note> 
                  <hi>To whom Preaching, and Offering at the Lords table do belong to them alſo carefull ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and governing the Church doth appertaine.</hi> Againe he ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">pag. 162. 108. 202.</note> 
                  <hi>Theſe ſelf ſame perſons that were in one, were in all theſe actions: and the Churches were governed by the common counſell of the Presbyters.</hi> And<note n="“" place="margin">pag. 133.</note> 
                  <hi>The Apoſtle ioyneth both theſe properties in good Pastors.</hi> And<note n="*" place="margin">pag. 111.</note> 
                  <hi>They must be trusted with both or with neither.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Now touching all this Gods word chargeth vs expreſly ſaying:</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Col. 4.17 Rom. 12.7</note> 
                  <hi>Take heed to your Ministery which you haue receaved in the Lord, to fulfill it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">But to this our Churches order is cleane contrary by reaſon of our Dioceſan ruling Biſhops. We may not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill our Miniſtery for them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Therfore our Churches order in reſpect of our Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan ruling Biſhops is cleane contrary to Gods word. And therefore of neceſſitie heerein we ought to be reformed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Where yet I can not but note,<note place="margin">Note.</note> how by our owne Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment law this is wholy yeelded to every ordinary Paſtor in England. As namely where the booke of Ordination
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:21672:23"/>maketh every one of them to vndertake<note n="*" place="margin">Booke of Ordinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Printed Ann. 1596</note> 
                  <hi>to minister the Doctrine and Sacraments and Diſcipline of Christ as the Lord hath commanded, and as this Realme hath receaved the ſame ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the commandements of God.</hi> Though it ſaith, <hi>as this Realme hath receaved the ſame;</hi> Yet we muſt marke that it ſaith not ſo ſimplie, but with ſpeciall reſtraint, <hi>according to the commandements of God.</hi> Yea before alſo it requireth <hi>the Diſcipline of Christ to be ministred</hi> in ſuch maner <hi>as the Lord hath commanded.</hi> So that heere this reſtriction and certaine direction is ſet downe expreſly twice for fayling. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lawes intent and meaning is not heere to do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, much leſſe<note n="“" place="margin">Act. Parl. Henr. 8. Ann. 25. cap. 19.</note> againſt the order ſet down in Gods word, but to do according to it. And not to take from Paſtors the ordinary power of Eccleſiaſticall Dicipline (as now the practiſe is) but to giue it them. Namely if Gods word do giue it them; which we ſaw before that it doth. God forbid therefore that we in England now ſhould be<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 19.6.</note> bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from the ordinance of God in his word, this being alſo the true intent of our owne Lawes.</p>
               <p>If our Adverſaries will ſay that this bringeth in a paritie of Miniſters. And we can not be ignorant that our moſt wiſe and Noble King profeſſeth his miſlike of the paritie of Miniſters.</p>
               <p>I anſwere with all reverence and ſubmiſſion to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, that I conceaue his meaning not to be againſt the paritie which before I haue ſpoken of. And as for a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall paritie we miſlike and deteſt it alſo. Yea in a ſort we ſay that the Churches ſtate is Monarchicall. For we af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme that in every ſeverall true Church there ought to be a diſparitie of Church Miniſters: viz. the Paſtor aboue the Elders, and the Elders aboue the Deacons,<note place="margin">ad Smyrne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> as <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſaith. And in Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ferences &amp; Synods where many Paſtors
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:21672:24"/>meet, we do not only allow but require a diſparitie and prioritie alſo, namely in the Preſident or Moderator. Yea we do not ſimply diſallow a continuing Preſident, ſo that his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance be ſubiect to his Brethrens free liking, they ſeeing it to be not againſt the glorie of God and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon good. And for all this we are well aſſured there is ſound warrant in the word of God. But as touching a farther diſparitie then this, We anſwer, comparing Paſtors with Paſtors among themſelves in their common office, or in any of the naturall parts therof, we ſee not how there may be any diſparitie or difference in them. May one Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of peace permit the reſt in the ſame Countie to call before them, to reproue and rebuke Malefactors, but not in any wiſe to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit to priſon, or to bind in recognizance any man? May one aſſume this power alone to himſelfe, and exclude all the reſt? Surely this were in the common wealth arrogant, iniurious, and vnlawful without expreſſe warrant from the ſame authoritie by which they all hold their Offices. How much more vnlawfull is it for men without Gods warrant to preſume in Gods matters in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering and changing, in making greater or leſſer the Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall offices of Chriſts Church? <hi>Magis</hi> and <hi>Minus</hi> in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon reaſon can not be admitted in the nature of one and the ſame Office, what<note n="*" place="margin">Is one King more a king, then an other? One Father more a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then an other?</note> Office ſoever we ſpeake of. But this is ſo, more ſpecially in the Eccleſiaſticall. For it is excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtrange that among true and proper Paſtors ſom ſhould be more, ſom leſſe Paſtors: which yet muſt needes be, if ſom may have more ſom leſſe Paſtorall power. The vnreaſonablenes heereof appeareth further if we conſider in like manner the nature and condicion of the Viſible Churches. One Viſible Church can not bee more a Church then any other, though ſom may be greater ſom
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:21672:24"/>ſmaller, ſom richer ſom poorer. Yet as Churches they are all equally Churches, and one hath as much Eccleſiaſticall or ſpirituall right, power, &amp; authoritie, as any other. Even ſo is it with their Paſtors, being compared (I ſaye) togea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as Paſtors among themſelves. Againe as the Apoſtles were all equall Apoſtles; ſo ſurely the Paſtors ought to be, who are in deed their right &amp; proper Succeſſors. <hi>Pari con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſortio prediti &amp; honoris &amp; potestatis.</hi> As <hi>Cyprian</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">cypr. de vnit. Eccleſ.</note> ſaith: <hi>The Apostles were indued with equall honor &amp; power.</hi> Therfore the Paſtors their Succeſſors ought to be ſo likewiſe. To which purpoſe alſo is that in the ſame place following.<note n="“" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                  <hi>Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius vnus est, cuius à ſingulis in ſolidum pars tenetur.</hi> There is but one kinde or nature of the Biſhoplie or Paſtoral office, whereof everie one participateth in whole. And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place,<note n="*" place="margin">Cypr. in Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cil. Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thag.</note> 
                  <hi>Nemo nostrum Epiſcopum Epiſcoporum ſe facit: None of vs maketh him ſelf a Biſhop of Biſhops,</hi> or over Biſhops. Signifying that it was not lawfull for them ſo to be: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther likewiſe a Paſtor over Paſtors. And to what purpoſe els is that of <hi>Ierome</hi> to <hi>Evagrius,</hi> where ſpeaking of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops or Paſtors ſaith he,<note n="“" place="margin">Icrom ad Evagr.</note> 
                  <hi>Eiuſdem ſunt meriti, eiuſdem Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotij. They are all of one and the ſame preeminence, of one and the ſame Office.</hi> Theſe ſentences are verie memorable, ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to allow ordinarie equalitie in all Offices which are of one and the ſame kinde or nature. Howſoever yet a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination from the right and perfect Paſtorall office began to come in, in the dayes of theſe men, &amp; alſo to get allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance even of the moſt famous Doctors, ſpecially about <hi>Ieromes</hi> dayes. Whereby it is manifeſt how a paritie of Paſtors ought to be held, and yet notwithſtanding how a paritie of all Miniſters ought not to be in any Church.</p>
               <p>But ſome wil ſay, this is not enough. For this neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les will be the cauſe of ſtrife &amp; diſcord in the Churches.</p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:21672:25"/>
               <p>We anſwer, The cleane contrarie is true. Your humane diſparitie in the Eccleſiaſticall Miniſteries both is and ever<note n="*" place="margin">Nazianz. in orat poſt redi.</note> hath ben the true cauſe of diſcord. But our Divine diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritie, that which we hold and allow, is the true cauſe of peace and vnitie. For where, in what place can diſcord be? In every Church we acknowledg a Superior, and in everie meeting out of many Churches a Superior likewiſe. Now no other place can be imagined where diſcord and ſtrife Eccleſiaſticall can ariſe. If therefore Superioritie and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paritie will cauſe peace, wee through Gods goodnes and bleſſing ſhall both have and keepe peace every where. If a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie other Superioritie bee required, and namely Yours, which croſſeth yea cutteth of Gods owne ordinance in the Paſtoral office, we deny that it can ever procure peace. And this our preſent experience doth ſhew in all the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Reformed Churches compared with ous. They all inioying this ordinance of God have moſt admirable vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. We only wanting this, notwithſtanding many &amp; ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie worldly advantages, yet do remaine ſtill (now theſe 50. yeeres almoſt) in wofull diſſentions, deſolations, and diſſipations. Neither can the Lordly Prelacie, neither will they remedy it.</p>
               <p>If heerein yet men will not be ſatisſied, but will hold it ſtill to be ſpeciall wiſedom to take away from ſom Paſtors the power of ſpirituall governement, and to give it to ſom few. We anſwer againe with the holy Ghoſt, It behoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth vs not, it is high preſumption<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 4.6.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>to be wiſe aboue</hi> (much rather contrary to) <hi>that which is written.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:21672:25"/>
               <head>Reaſon 5.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">THOSE Elders or Paſtors (as they cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t themſelves) ſtand directlie contrarie to Gods word,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Lord-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters.</note>
                  <hi> who do rule their fellow-Elders or Paſtors (and ſpecially manie whole Churches) with a Lordly Eccleſiaſticall power, or ſole authoritie: alſo who do rule them Civilly with out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward force and compulſive power: and who receave Civil Titles and Stiles anſwering to the worldly honor due to high Magiſtrates in the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">But our Dioceſan Biſhops in England are ſuch Elders or Paſtors, and do thus rule and ſtand by their publike Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice or Offices which they hold.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore our Dioceſan Biſhops in England even by their publike Office or Offices which they hold, ſtand di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to Gods word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Propoſition (whereof only there can be doubt) is proved by many plaine places of Gods word. Chriſt ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly forbad his Apoſtles this whole matter (and in them much more all other Miniſters their inferiors) in theſe words:<note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 20.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Ye know that the Rulers of the Nations haue dominion over them, and the Great men exerciſe authoritie over them. But it ſhall not be ſo among you. But who ſoever will be great among you, let him be your ſervant.</hi> Luke hath the ſame thus:<note n="“" place="margin">Luke. 22.25.</note> 
                  <hi>The Kings of the Nations haue dominion, or rule as Lords over them; and they who exerciſe authoritie over them are called Gratious Lords. But ye ſhall not be ſo.</hi> And Peter an Elder (as he calleth himſelfe) chargeth all Elders that they be not<note n="*" place="margin">1 Pet. 5.8.</note> 
                  <hi>as Lords over Gods heritage, but examples to the flocke.</hi> And Paul re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth it for his part, ſaying,<note n="“" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.24.</note> 
                  <hi>Not that we haue dominion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ver your faith, but are helpers of your ioy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere it is a ſilly evaſion (which ſom vſe) or rather a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſion
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:21672:26"/>of theſe manifeſt Scriptures, to ſay; Chriſt heere for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth his Apoſtles to expect Civill power &amp; authoritie by vertue of their Eccleſiaſticall Miniſterie: or, it is heere denyed that Civil power is neceſſarily annexed to the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall function. And beſides this that nothing els i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> heere denyed by our Savior to his Apoſtles and Miniſters. I ſay this is a vaine ſhift. The Apoſtles manifeſtly deſired this outward preeminence no other way but by Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from Chriſt, whom they hoped ſhould haue ben a great Prince in the world. This<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 20.21. Marc. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</note> they ſimply deſired and this Chriſt ſimply denied, both to them and in them to all true Miniſters of Chriſt for ever. Beſides <hi>Luke</hi> alſo addeth the Magnificent Titles of worldy authoritie, and theſe to be likewiſe denyed them. Which indeed neceſſarily fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth. Finally both <hi>Mathew</hi> &amp; <hi>Luke</hi> do principally ſpeake of the forbidding of Civill rule to Miniſters, yet their words are ſo generall that we muſt needs grant, that Chriſt there forbiddeth his Miniſters ſimply &amp; generally al Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly rule, or domination, or ſole authoritie whatſoever. And therefore Eccleſiaſticall domination or ſole authoritie in Church matters alſo. Even as it is manifeſt that <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>Paul</hi> do (without controverſy) in the places before rehear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. It is no better ſhift, to ſay that Chriſt heere forbad nothing but Tyrannicall over-ruling of the brethren. Or only the ambitious deſire of Lordly rule, ſole power, and civill authoritie: but not the things themſelues.</p>
               <p>But all this <hi>D. Bilſon</hi> alone (though now he be a L. Biſhop himſelfe) hath moſt fully and ſubſtantially confuted. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Ieſuits and Seminaries obiecting thus <hi>[The word is</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Math. 20.25.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>they Over-rule their Subiects with iniusticę and violence. You ſhall not do ſo.]</hi> He replyeth,<note n="“" place="margin">D. Bilſ. againſt the Apol. of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Seminar. part. 2. pag. 174. print. Lond. 1586.</note> 
                  <hi>So your new Tranſlation over-ruleth the word. Howbeit Christ in that place
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:21672:26"/>doth not traduce the Power of Princes as vniuſt and outragious, but distinguiſheth the calling of his Apostles from the maner of regiment which God hath allowed the Magistrat. Christ ſaith not Princes be tyrants, you ſhall deale more curteouſly then they do: but he ſaith Princes be Lords and rulers over their people by Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance you ſhall not be ſo. Againe the word which S. Luke hath, is</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>without any compoſition; They be Lords &amp; Masters: and S. Paul confeſſeth of himſelfe and other Apostles, Not that we be Lords or Masters of your faith. Ye the compound</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>is with power &amp; force to rule men whether they will or no, not with wrong and iniury to oppreſſe them. And therefore the concluſion is inevitable, that Princes may lawfully compell and puniſh their Subiects, which Biſhops may not.</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Pag. 175.</note> 
                  <hi>All Pastors and Biſhops are ſtraitly charged not to medle with the ſword.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 182.</note> 
                  <hi>To compell Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes and Schiſmatikes neither is it poſsible ſor the Preacher if he would, nor lawfull if he could: he lacketh both meanes and leave to constraine them. Biſhops be flatly forbidden to raigne, and must not meddle with the materiall ſword.</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Pag. 227.</note> 
                  <hi>Commanding and forcing our Savior forbiddeeh to all his Diſciples.</hi> Where the full effect of all his diſcourſe is this: <hi>All Civill i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>riſdiction and power of the ſword to commaund, compell, and puniſh by loſſe of life, limme, or libertie, is ſecluded from the Ministers function and reſerved to the Magistrates.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 22.24.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Christ preciſely forbad his Apostles to beare rule and exerciſe authoritie over their brethren: not vniust and tyrannicall rule, but all compulſive power.</hi> And <hi>where the thing is not lawfull, the ſigne is not lawfull. &amp;c.</hi> To like purpoſe alſo he writeth in his booke of the Perpetual Governement of Chriſtes Church:<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 137.142.</note> where he ſaith, † <hi>Many giftes may conioyne in one man, many offices cannot.</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Pag. 52.</note> 
                  <hi>The Miniſters ſhall not have any ſuch rule or dominion as the great States have.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 55.</note> 
                  <hi>The thing ſo much prohibited by Christ &amp; his Apostles, is, that Preachers &amp; Pastors ſhould</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>behave or thinke themſelves to bee Lords
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:21672:27"/>and Maiſters over their brethren.</hi> And<note n="“" place="margin">Pag. 56.</note> 
                  <hi>To increaſe the love of the ſheepe toward their Sheepheards, Christ would not have his Apoſtles to be feared as Maiſters, but to be honored as Fathers; and conſequently Paſtors not to force, but to feede; not to chaſe, but to lead the flocke committed to their charge; neither roughly to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat them as ſervants, but gently to perſwade them as coheires of the ſame kingdome.</hi> Heere are Teſtimonies of this man for vs moſt full, moſt cleare, and above all exception.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſon 6.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">IF in the Lawes eſtimation the calling of Miniſters with vs is given by thoſe who in Gods word have no power to give it,<note place="margin">Vſurpation</note> then this is contrarie to Gods word and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarie to be reformed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">But in the Lawes eſtimation the calling of Miniſters with vs is given by thoſe who in Gods worde have no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to give it.</hi> Namely it is given by a Dioceſan ruling Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, who is no where found (as before I ſhewed) in al the New Teſtament. So that he can not therein have anie power or authoritie to give Miniſters their calling, nor yet to take it from them. Againe by the rule of Gods word that particular Church whiche is to have the Miniſter, ought to be preſent and to ſhew a liking and conſent in their Miniſters calling. Whiche proveth that no Biſhop hath any power or authoritie in Gods word to give anie Miniſter his calling, or to take it from him in abſence of that Church to whom the Miniſter belongeth, yea and (as the practiſe now is) vtterly without their liking.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore this, that is the giving of the Miniſters cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with vs by ſuch as now do give it and in ſuch maner, is contrary to Gods word, and ought of neceſſitie to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:21672:27"/>
               <p>Where I ſay; by the rule of Gods worde,<note place="margin">The Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches right.</note> that Church which is to have the Miniſter ought to bee preſent and to ſhew a liking and conſent in their Miniſters Calling: this is evident by many teſtimonies, and reaſons. Firſt, becauſe in the Apoſtles time the Church had a conſent in Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, as it appeareth to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> where the Apoſtle ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 5.4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>I have determined already, when yee are gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red together and my ſpirit, in the name of our L. Ieſus Christ, that ſuch a one, by the power of our L. Ieſus Chriſt, be delivered to Satan.</hi> And,<note n="*" place="margin">vers 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Put away from among your ſelves that wicked man.</hi> Which agreeth with Chriſtes owne ordinance and precept, where he ſaith,<note n="“" place="margin">Mat. 18.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Tell the Church: If he heare not the Church, let him be vnto thee as an Heathen and a Publicane.</hi> Now if the Church was to Excommunicate, ſurelie the Church alſo was to elect her Miniſters. For theſe are the 2. maine partes of the holy Governement Eccleſiaſticall, both which muſt belong to the Church equallie &amp; alike. Further it is apparant by the Apoſtles practiſe. Firſt, the calling of <hi>Matthias</hi> to the Apoſtleſhip was permitted (ſo farre as was poſſible) to the Churches Election. For they<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 1.23 &amp;c.</note> appointed two, whereof one ſhould be and was divinely choſen. This queſtionles was done (not of neceſſitie for that Calling which was then to be given, but only) for an example in Eccleſiaſticall Elections which the Churches after ſhould and did imitate. Beſides, howſoever the very Election of <hi>Matthias</hi> was by Divine lot, yet it was all done in the Churches preſence with the actuall concurrence of their prayers and free conſentes inſtantly. Now theſe acts of the Church as they may, ſo therefore they ought to be perpetual in every Election of whatſoever Miniſter; ſeeing even for that end the Apoſtles cauſed nowe the Church thus to do. It is a ſlight anſwer and vntrue, to ſay,<note n="“" place="margin">Parpet. govern. pag. 69.</note> 
                  <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:21672:28"/>are no preceptes.</hi> For the ſame anſwerer elſwhere confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth, that<note n="*" place="margin">Per. gov. pag. 373.</note> 
                  <hi>the Apoſtles taught the Church by their Example.</hi> But if he had not confeſſed it, yet the trueth of this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall point is in it ſelfe moſt certain. Wherefore was the Booke of the <hi>Apoſtles Actes</hi> els written? But that their Acts in the Churches ſhould be Rules and patterns for vs to do likewiſe. All Divines vſe the Argument drawen from an act of Chriſt or his Apoſtles, and vrge it even to bind vs no les then if it were a formall Precept. And ſo we read that Chriſt himſelf &amp; his Apoſtles too, reaſoned ſundry times from the bare Actes of the Prophetes and men of God in the old Law. I know in divers Examples there are to be found <hi>Circumſtances</hi> which fit not all times, places, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. What then? Neither do Precepts commonly fit vs in ſo generall a maner. By this ſhift then we may avoid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe and direct Precepts alſo. And thus ſcarce any thing in Gods word ſhall ſuffice to conſtrayne and binde vs. Wherefore alwayes we vrge no other Exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, or not in any other points, then ſuch as do and may fit vs continually, and every where, even ſo well as they fitted thoſe of old. In which caſe it is a miſerable denyall to ſay, Examples are no precepts. God graunt vs and all true Chriſtians, to inioy our Churches ordered after the Apoſtles examples, and to have all other Cuſtomes of men (when once we diſcerne them) vtterly abandoned. But to proceed a litle: The Apoſtles again<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 6.3.5.6.</note> charged the Church at <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to chooſe their Deacons: therfore much more ought the Churches (who are not ignorant beaſtes, but men taught of God) to chooſe their Paſtors. Laſtly, they<note n="“" place="margin">Act. 14.23.</note> ordeyned Elders to ſundrie Churches which were actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allie preſent and conſenting. So much is moſt evident by the very text: neither can any except againſt this; which
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:21672:28"/>ſuffiſeth our purpoſe. So that it is vaine where<note n="*" place="margin">Perpet. gov. pag. 70.</note> ſome con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende that this worde <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> heere vſed will not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarilie prove that the Churches did elect their Elders. I anſwer, this very woord (yea thus as it is heere co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrued) is not ſo weak for our purpoſe as is pretended. For we find the ſame word in good Authors, having the very like Gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticall conſtruction, that is, ioyned not with the people, but with the Guides or principal in the aſſemblie. And yet the very nature of this word (ſignifying in the ordinarie vſe thereof the cuſtome which was then to give Voices by lifting vp of handes) implyeth the Peoples concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and voyce-giving iointly with the Guides of the aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie. For aſmuch as this geſture of lifting vp handes for voyce-giving in the the publicke meetinges did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes and moſt chieflie concerne the People. In this very manner to this purpoſe we have this word in <hi>Demoſthenes:</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Timocr.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Which of the Lawes the Nomothetae (which were the principall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors) ſhall ordayne or constitute by lifting vp of handes the ſame is ratified.</hi> Where notwithſtanding, the Lifting vp of hands (as is well knowen) was not the <hi>Nomothetaes</hi> or chief Authors part only: but the Peoples act is vnderſtood alſo by implication. Whoſe part was chiefly to Lift vp handes, eyther before or after the <hi>Nomothetaes</hi> act. Even ſo likewiſe this ſame worde vſed heere in the <hi>Actes</hi> in the very ſame maner ſhall import the Peoples part alſo: viz. a preſent co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the appointing of their Elders, though only their Guides the Apoſtles voyce-giving and ordayning of them be named. But we will not preſſe this. We may (as I ſaid) cleane omit this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſideration, and yet this text in the <hi>Actes</hi> doth fully ſerve our mayne purpoſe. Namely it proveth fully that theſe Elders were ordayned by the Apoſtles in
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:21672:29"/>the preſence and with the free liking of the ſeverall Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. Another conceite there is, that the ſenſe of this word heere is the ſame which the Greeke Eccleſiaſtical Writers long after do vſe it in: viz. <hi>only to lay on hands in Ordination,</hi> and no more. It is an idle conceite. All do know, that the later Eccleſiaſticall Greeke Writers have altered the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and proper vſe of this word, as they (yea and the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines alſo) have done in other: as after we<note n="*" place="margin">In the 2. Aſſertion &amp; 9. Reaſon in the end thereof.</note> ſhal further ſee. In the Apoſtles time they ſpake the ordinarie and knowen phraſe taken from the former times. But then no man vſed this word in ſuch ſenſe. They which followed ſom hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares, can not prove that the Ancients ſpake like the after-commers. Wherefore, to our purpoſe againe: By all theſe textes thus declared, it remayneth evident that the Church, which is to have a Miniſter, ought to be preſent and to ſhew liking and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent freely to their Miniſters cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling: ſith we have ſeene that it was ſo in the practiſe of the Apoſtles, and by the ordinance of Chriſt. Which alſo (it ſeemeth) our very <hi>Book of Ordinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi> (which is by Law) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendeth &amp; requireth, where it ſaith, <hi>Take thou authority, &amp;c. in this Congregation.</hi> The word, <hi>this,</hi> importeth that the very particular Congregation wherein he ſhould haue autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, ſhould be preſent. And why ſhould they neceſſarily be preſent, but freely to conſent? Alſo heere by it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that the Law would not that any Miniſter ſhould be ordained but to a certain Congregation. All which good, neceſſary, and Chriſtian rules how they be now every where broken &amp; deſpiſed, who ſeeth not? Yea though the manifeſt intent of our Law doth require them. A word more let vs add touching <hi>D. Bilſons</hi> approbatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> alſo of the Churches free conſent in choſing their Paſtors. Whoſe teſtimony I do delight to apply to our purpoſe for divers
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:21672:29"/>good conſiderations.<note n="“" place="margin">D <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ilſ a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minar part. 2. pag. 353.356.</note> Saith he, <hi>We haue the words and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of the H. Ghost for that which we ſay, &amp;c. viz. that the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple can and ought to diſcerne and try the doctrines and ſpirits of the Teachers; and ſo to choſe and refuſe them, as they by the word ſhould ſee good.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">pag. 355.</note> 
                  <hi>How can the People do either, if they haue not ſkill and leave to diſcerne both.</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Perpet. gover pag. 360.</note> 
                  <hi>The Apostles left elections in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently to the People and Clergie at Ieruſalem. The People had as much right to choſe their Pastors, as the Clergie that had more ſkill to iudge</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 339.</note> 
                  <hi>Well may the Peoples intereſt ſtand vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the grounds of reaſon and nature, and be derived from the rules of Christian equitie.</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Pag. 359.</note> 
                  <hi>The late Biſhops of Rome</hi> have not ceaſed <hi>curſing &amp; fighting, till excluding both Prince and People they reduced the election wholy to the Clergie.</hi> But he telleth them, <hi>by their leave it was not ſo from the beginning.</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>30.</note> 
                  <hi>I acknowledge each Church &amp; people ſtand free by Gods law to admit, maintaine, &amp; obey no man as their Pastor without their liking.</hi> It is true he addeth this, vnles <hi>by law, custome, or conſent they restraine themſelves.</hi> But this he himſelfe elſwhere anſwereth roundly:<note n="“" place="margin">Pag. 22 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>What au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie had others after the Apostles deathes to chaunge the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike governement?</hi> And ſuch additions he calleth<note n="†" place="margin">Pag. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions of times, inventions of men, and a tranſgreſsing of the Commaundement of God for the traditions of men.</hi> And a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he calleth this plainly<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 11 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Intruſion,</hi> and <hi>Preſumption.</hi> This ſufficeth to ſhew, that he well vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth the truth in this cauſe.</p>
               <p>But now it wilbe demanded: How can we then allow the Calling of the Miniſters in England, iudging them by the rule of Gods worde. I anſwere; Firſt this is ever a ſure ground (not in the Schooles only, but) with all faithfull Chriſtians reaſoning about any matter: <hi>Conſequens incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modum non ſolvit argumentum. An inconvenient conſequence taketh not away an Argument.</hi> We muſt not then decline
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:21672:30"/>from the truth for any inconvenience which may follow. Rather it behoveth vs to looke well to our ſelves &amp; to our profeſſion and ſtanding wherein we abide, and Chriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with ſpeed to amend our error. Howbeit I ſpeak not this, as if I abſolutly denied the whole Calling of our Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. I do not ſo. The Lord knoweth there is none in England more vnwilling to runne vpon this rocke then I am. And yet nevertheles I dare not, I can not, (nor anie good Chriſtian els) agree to change Gods Ordinances af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our occaſions. Wherefore I anſwer to this queſtion thus. For my part, I beleeve that the true ratification and warrant of our Miniſters calling which is by Gods word, ſtandeth in this, &amp; only in this,<note place="margin">The Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation. See Bez. in Act, 14.23.</note> that our Viſible Churches do conſent and accept them whom they receave for ſuch. I ſay, they do conſent and accept them, after what ſort ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever it be done. And this their conſent, I acknowledge, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth them (before God) their Miniſtery, though conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with many, great, &amp; publike corruptions otherwayes.</p>
               <p>In which reſpect the Papiſtes are ſoundly anſwered, who calumniat our Miniſtery as if either we had none at all, or els had that which we have from them. Againe this anſwereth others, who becauſe in our publike orders there are many evills ioyned with our Miniſters Calling which are not to be iuſtified, nor to be communicated with, and becauſe they are commonly eſteemed to have their Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling from theſe vnlawfull meanes, viz. from the Dioceſan ruling Biſhops without the Church, though in deed it be not ſo: therefore they do wholy and abſolutly deny the Miniſterie in England, which in trueth and by good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they ought not to do abſolutly and altogeather. How beit yet I ſpeak not this in favor to ſuch perſons or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations among vs, which do evidently appeare to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:21672:30"/>of wilfulnes Chriſtes Ordinances, and to ſpeak evil of the way of God. Toward ſuch I can not deny but the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 19.9. 1 Tim. 6.5,</note> pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> and precept ought to bee followed, who teacheth in this caſe, ſaying, "<hi>Separate from ſuch.</hi>
                  <note n="†" place="margin">Ephe. 5.12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 6.19.</note> 
                  <hi>Have n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> fellowſhip with the vnfruitfull workes of darknes. * Touch no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thing.</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Marke them which cauſe ſchiſmes and ſcandalles beſide the doctrine which you have learned, and avoid them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſon 7.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">TO wantany maine part of the</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> Luke 12.42<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note>
                  <hi> ordinary appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted meanes of ſalvation is</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Math. 28.20. Iſa. 30.21.</note>
                  <hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to Gods word and neceſſarie to be reformed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">But the right and true Diſcipline Eccleſiaſticall in <hi>each proper Viſible Church,</hi> is one maine part of the ordinary meanes of ſalvation</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 18.17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ioh. 20.23. Mat. 16.19<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>appointed by God for every ſoule: and this we in England do vtterly want.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore we in England in reſpect of Diſcipline and Governement Eccleſiaſticall do ſtand contrarie to Gods word, and ought heerein neceſſarily to be reformed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Or thus.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Where the Apoſtles true Suceeſſors are ſpoyled of their Office and Miniſterie of <hi>binding and looſing, forgiving &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning</hi> of ſcandalous ſinnes, there is grievous Sacrilege, &amp; there ought to be of neceſſitie a reformation to reſtore them to this their ſpirituall</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Math. 18.18. Ioh. 20.23.</note>
                  <hi> right and duty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">But the ordinarie Paſtors and Teachers of all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in England are the Apoſtles true Succeſſors, and they are ſpoyled of the office of <hi>binding and looſing, forgiving and retayning</hi> the ſcandalous ſinnes of their owne flockes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore the ordinarie Paſtors and Teachers of all the Churches in England do ſuffer the wrong of ſacrilege,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:21672:31"/>and ought of Neceſſitie to be reſtored to this their ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all right and dutie which yet they are held from.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label>Or thus.</label>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Where the Apoſtles true Succeſſors are barred from v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 16.19.</note> both the Keyes which Chriſt himſelfe gave them &amp; put them in truſt with all, there the vſe of both ought to be reſtored to them. Otherwiſe<note n="†" place="margin">2 Tim. 1.14. Tim. 6.20.14. Cor. 9.17 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6.</note> how can they ſay in their conſciences before God that they walke in their calling, and fulfill their Miniſtery, and diſcharge their truſt? And how can the flocke aſſuredly expect that Heaven ſhal be opened to them?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">But the ordinaric Paſtors and Teachers in all the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in England are the Apoſtles true and only Succeſſors among vs, and they are barred fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſing one of the Keyes, namely the Key of power or governement, as it is called.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore the vſe of this Key alſo ought of neceſſitie to be reſtored to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <p>Obedience is better then ſacrifice,</p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>1.</hi> Samu. <hi>15.22.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p>If ye know theſe things, bleſſed are ye if ye do them,</p>
                  <bibl>Ioh. <hi>13.17.</hi>
                  </bibl>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reaſon 8.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſt out Prophet &amp; King.</note>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">WHOSOEVER denyeth Chriſt the Saviour to be our intire and perfect Prophet and ſpirituall King (by taking away from him ſom parts of his Propheticall and Kingly Offices, and aſcribing the ſame vnto Men) he disniniſheth the honor &amp; dignitie of Chriſt, he impugneth the Foundation of ſaving faith, and is<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 3.11. Act. 4.12. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>4.6.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to Gods word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">But the Dioceſan Biſhops, &amp;c. do (by neceſſary conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce) deny Chriſt the Saviour to be our perfect Prophet and ſpiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uall King by taking fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him ſom proper partes of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:21672:31"/>his Propheticall and Kingly Offices. For they hold ſound and intire only Chriſtes Prieſtly Office. Brieflie, as the Catholikes do ioyne Men with Chriſt in all theſe 3. Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, ſo do our Dioceſans in the 2. former.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore the Dioceſan ruling Biſhops, &amp;c. do diminiſh the honor and dignitie of Chriſt, they impugne the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of ſaving faith, and are contrarie to Gods word.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Propoſition</hi> if it be wiſely conſidered, is playne. For it can not be doubted, but Chriſt Ieſus hath 3. Offices: viz. he is our Prophet, King, and Prieſt; &amp; by vertue of all theſe 3. properly he is our Saviour and Mediator. Againe we are neceſſarily to believe that Chriſt Ieſus hath in his owne onely perſon all theſe 3. Offices intire, abſolut, and perfect. In ſo much that if any ſhall (with what colour ſoever) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate theſe Offices to others, denying them to Chriſts ſole and proper perſon, or any of them, yea or any mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt and certaine part of them; the ſame verily do impugne the foundation of ſaving faith, and deprive Chriſt of a part of his ſole and proper glorie. Where alſo I deſire it may be remembred, that Chriſt Ieſus though he properly worketh our Redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only by his Prieſtly Office, that is, only by the Sacrifice of his owne ſufferings; yet he wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth our Salvation and accompliſheth his Mediation not but by all theſe 3. his Offices iointly togeather. So that it is the error of a nomber who thinke; to beleeve only that Chriſt dyed for vs, this is enough to ſalvation. We need not to regard in Chriſt any more. Whereby men co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie forget the other partes of Chriſtes glorious worke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward vs, viz. his holy compleat <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and <hi>Governement.</hi> But both theſe alſo ought to be believed &amp; yeelded vnto the perſon of our Saviour Chriſt intirely &amp; wholy, even in reſpect as he is our Saviour &amp; Mediator; no leſſe then the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:21672:32"/>other, that he perfectly ſuffered for vs as our Redeemer. This is well to be conſidered.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Aſſumption</hi> our adverſaries do make to be true. For they take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt perſonally a manifeſt part of his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall Office: and likewiſe of his Kingly Office. It is a part of Chriſtes owne proper Propheticall Office to teach vs with authoritie by him ſelfe<note n="*" place="margin">Proved in Reaſon 1. pa. 1.2 &amp;c. And Heb. 3.2, 3, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, 6. Math. 17.5 Iohn. 14.6. and 16.13.</note> alone in his owne word and Teſtament the outward forme, nature, and conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (which is but one) of all his Viſible Churches whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Countries rich or poore, Monarchies or Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craties, &amp;c: likewiſe all the true Eccleſiaſticall Offices and Miniſteries in them, with every kinde of action and thing properly Eccleſiaſticall vſed in the Church, or where ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver els Religiouſly. Alſo it is a part of his proper Kinglie Office,<note n="“" place="margin">Matth. 6.33. and 22.2. &amp;c. Luke 19.14. 27. Iam. 4.12. 1 Cor. 12.5 Mat. 18.17 Iohn 20.23.</note> by him ſelfe to conſtitute and inioyne the ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and only true forme of all his Viſible Churches, and to admit wherſoever none other; ſpiritually to rule, to guide, and to bleſſe vs in them only, by his owne Miniſteries and Ordinances inſtituted by him ſelfe or by his Spirite in his Apoſtles, and by none other. All which the foreſaide Dioceſeſan ruling Biſhops, &amp;c. do take from Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe perſonally, and do<note n="*" place="margin">D. Whit-gift againſt Mai. Cart-wright, pa. 370.376.</note> permit them vnto Men. Saying, it is indifferent (and ſomwhere ſomtimes convenient) for Chriſtians thus to do. Therefore the <hi>Aſſumption</hi> is true.</p>
               <p>It wilbe ſaid, if this be ſo, then likewiſe the ancient Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters <hi>Austine, Ambroſe, Chryſostome, Leo, Gregorie, &amp;c.</hi> did erre in faith to ſalvation, and believed not ſom partes of the fundamentall Offices of Chriſt our Savior. For thoſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientes did hold ſundry Eccleſiaſticall Inventions of men, beſides that they were the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelves Dioceſan ruling Biſhops. Wherefore (by this reaſon) they diminiſhed not a little of our Saviors moſt holy &amp; healthfull Offices, both Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheticall
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:21672:32"/>and Kingly. Which to affirme wilbe very hard. The ſame muſt be ſaide likewiſe of our late bleſſed Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, <hi>Cranmer, Ridley, Latimer, Ferrar, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I anſwer, we embrace theſe holy men of God (both the elder and later) for their other manifolde teſtimonies of pietie. Therefore we iudge them as faithfull ſervantes of Chriſt according to that meaſure of light wherein they li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. That is, they did generally and indiſtinctly beleeve and profeſſe ſoundly all the whole Offices of Chriſt to ſalvatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yet true it is they erred in theſe foreſaid external partes pertayning to Chriſtes Prophecie and Kingdome through the common ſway of the times then: the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of iniquitie (that is Antichriſt) advancing it ſelfe day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie very much even by them, and by theſe their errors, though they for their partes were vnwitting &amp; vnwilling. The caſe thus ſtanding with them, we are not to doubt, but theſe their errors (though of them ſelves very great) were graciouſly pardoned in Chriſt: chiefly conſidering that theſe matters were not then examined nor any thing looked into; which with vs now theſe 40. yeeres have ben much debated, tried, and ſifted. Yea and by Gods worde are ſo cleerlie diſcovered, that we muſt needes now ſay, He that is ignorant let him be ignorant ſtil: and he that is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe let him be perverſe ſtill. Wherefore the condition of our Dioceſan L. Biſhops, &amp;c. in England, is farre vnlike at this day, and in no ſorte to be compared with that of thoſe Biſhops then. Ours have no excuſe, which they might have. <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaieth well in ſuch another caſe.<note n="*" place="margin">Cypri. Epi. 2.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Si quis de anteceſſoribus nostris vel ignoranter vel ſimpliciter non hoc ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervavit &amp; tenuit quod nos Dominus facere exemplo &amp; Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterio ſuo docuit potest ſimplicitati eius de indulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiâ Domini ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia concedi, nobis verò non poterit ignoſci qui nunc à Domino
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:21672:33"/>admoniti &amp; instructi ſumus. If any before vs either ignorantly or ſimply hath not obſerved and kept that which the Lord by his example &amp; doctrine hath taught vs to do, by the Lords mercy his ſimplicitie may be pardoned, but we cannot be forgiven who are now warned and instructed of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yet ſome will ſay, We can not ſhew any ſuch forme of a Viſible Church ſomtime for many hundreds of yeares togeather. Shall we then thinke that this is Chriſts perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall ordinance? I anſwere, firſt for 2. hundred yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Chriſt there is no man can ſhew any other forme of a Viſible Church (but this) any where in the whole world, as in the next <hi>Aſſertion</hi> preſently (God willing) we ſhall further ſee. Which (beſide the all-ſufficient word of God) is an excellent teſtimonie alſo: neither need we looke fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther into Humane writinges for the perpetuall neceſſitie heereof. Second: they who liſt to ſearch may finde argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes of divers particular Congregations being intire Viſible Churches in all ages, I thinke. Howbeit, what is that to vs? Muſt the Chriſtian faith or any part of it, ſtand or fall by the report of Mens ſtories? Or may we in this caſe conclude from them, Negatively? <hi>Mens writings men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not ſuch a Church at ſomtime. Therfore then there was none.</hi> And ſpecially to inferre thus; <hi>Therefore this is not Chriſts or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance alwayes neceſſarie for vs.</hi> To eſteeme mens writings ſo ſufficient as that by them we ſhould prove or diſprove a matter of Religion; I ſay, it is verie fooliſh at the leaſt.</p>
               <p>Finally our Adverſaries will obiect, that by theſe Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and defences we detract from the Kings authoritie &amp; power: namely thus miſliking that which he alloweth, &amp; ſpecially holding an authority Eccleſiaſticall not derived from him. I anſwer, even ſo did evill &amp; ſlanderous men accuſe the faithfull Chriſtians in the primitive age. They
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:21672:33"/>cryed that,<note n="*" place="margin">Act. 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Theſe all do against the decrees of Caeſar, ſaying that there is another King, one Ieſus.</hi> Our reply therefore vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them for this ſhall ſtand in 4. points. 1. We moſt glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> do<note n="*" place="margin">Math. 20.21.</note> 
                  <hi>give vnto Caeſar the things that are Caeſars, but to God the things that are Gods.</hi>
                  <note n="“" place="margin">Tertul. ad Scapula<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 2. <hi>Colimus Imperatorem vt homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> à Deo ſecundum, &amp; ſolo Deo minorem. We honor the King as a man next vnto God, and inferior to God only.</hi> 3. We glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> acknowledge that the King is, &amp; ought to be Supreme governor even in all cauſes and over all perſons Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall. Howbeit alwayes <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>non</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: <hi>Civilly, not Spiritually or Eccleſiastically.</hi> 4. The King is <hi>Custos &amp;</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> 
                  <hi>Vindex,</hi> the Keeper and Maintainer (by compulſive pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) of the whole ſtate of Religion. But he is not <hi>Author</hi> or <hi>Minister</hi> of any Eccleſiaſticall thing or Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitution what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever. Will our Adverſaries yeeld more? Or is not this ſufficient? I hope this ſhall ſuffice to ceaſe heerafter their ſlanders againſt vs in this cauſe. And thus much touching our firſt Aſſertion.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="assertion">
            <argument>
               <head>The 2. Aſſertion.</head>
               <p>For the ſpace of 200. yeares after Christ the Viſible Churches vſing governement were not Dioceſan Churches, but parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ordinary Congregations only: and the Biſhops (as they were particularly called after the Apostles) were only Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhionall not Dioceſan Biſhops, and differed from other Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors in Prioritie of order not in Maioritie of rule.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>IN this Aſſertion we obſerve 3. diſtinct partes. 1. A <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Church was then but one Ordinarie Congregation:
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:21672:34"/>and generally in each Citie then there was but one ſuch <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Congregation only. 2. The particular ordinary Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations had in themſelves their owne governement <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Eccleſiaſticall. 3. There was no Maioritie of rule, but Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oritie of order only, in a Biſhop then compared with other Paſtors.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="proof" n="1"/>
            <p>
               <label>The first is proved by theſe Testimonies following.</label>
            </p>
            <p>FIrſt let vs conſider that in the Apoſtles dayes the orday<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Elders<note n="“" place="margin">Citie by Citie. Tir. 1.5.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>&amp;<note n="*" place="margin">Church by Church, Act. 14.23.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was all one thing; namely becauſe in each Citie in thoſe times there were not many Churches in number, but one onely proper Church or Congregation of Chriſtians. Which alſo<note n="“" place="margin">Pag. 19.20</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue we further declared. Then for the next age after,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Anno 100</note> 
               <hi>Ignatius</hi> plainly ſheweth the common ſtate of the viſible Churches in this time alſo to be ſuch: where he thus wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth.<note n="†" place="margin">Ignat. ad Trall.</note> 
               <hi>Without a Biſhop, without a Senate of Elders, without Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons, &amp;c.</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Without theſe there is no Church, no company of of Saints, no holy Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation.</hi> Which proveth that then each Citie had but only one ordinary Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans. Sith doubtles each Citie then had but one ſuch Senat of Elders, and but one Biſhop, in <hi>Ignatius</hi> vnderſtanding. Further alſo he perſwading the Church of <hi>Philadelphia</hi> to vnitie and concord ſaith.<note n="“" place="margin">Ad Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladelph.</note> 
               <hi>I exhort you vſe one Faith, one Preaching, one ſupper of the Lord, &amp;c.</hi> For there is <hi>but one Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Table</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to the whole Church</hi> (heere in this Citie) <hi>and one Biſhop with a company of Elders and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons.</hi> Therefore in this Citie there was then but one Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Congregation of Chriſtians. Neither ſpeaketh he of this Church in <hi>Philadelphia</hi> as being of an other forme or conſtitution then other Churches then were, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed as being conformable and like to the maner of the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:21672:34"/>reſt. If we tranſlate <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> as ſom like better <hi>[to every Church]</hi> diſtributively, then our Aſſertion is more cleerely avouched. Againe touching the Church of <hi>Philadelphia</hi> he ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
               <hi>The Biſhop is Gods Ambaſſador to a people</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>that are togeather in one place.</hi> Laſtly writing elſwhere to the ſame effect he ſaith ſo much touching an other Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church, namely in the Citie <hi>Magneſia;</hi>
               <note n="“" place="margin">Ad Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſ.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. <hi>All of you com togeather into the fame place to prayer; Let there be but one common prayer, one minde, one hope, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iustin Martyr</hi> ſhewing the maner of the Churches wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipping <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of God in the Cities where they then were, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerveth the very ſame. Saith he;<note n="*" place="margin">Iuſt. Mart. Apolog. 2. Anno 142.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>On the Sonday as it is called All (the Christians) dwelling in the Cities, or abroad in the Country, do com togeather into the ſame place, &amp;c.</hi> It is very like that this was ſpecially ſpoken of the Church of Rome then: ſeeing there <hi>Iustin</hi> wrot and offered vp his Apologie to <hi>Antoninus</hi> the Emperor. Though with all he ſignifieth that he meanes other Churches in other<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and in Country-places likewiſe indifferently. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then, All the Chriſtians in each Citie (yea thoſe in Rome) made not divers but one conſtant and ordinary Congregation only.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Irenaeus</hi> in his time obſerveth no materiall difference <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> betweene <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Preſbyters</hi> Miniſters of the word. Which is a plaine argument that Biſhops then were not <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Biſhops overſeeing many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly diſtinct Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, but were Paſtors of one particular ordinary Congregation only. Thus he ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Irenae. lib. 3. cap. 3.</hi> Traditio vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. ſcripta: vel neceſſario con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequens ab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> quod eſt ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum per Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</note> 
               <hi>Traditio quae est ab Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolis per ſucceſsionem Preſbyterorum custoditur. The tradition which is taken from the Apostles is kept by ſucceſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Preſbyters.</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:21672:35"/>In the ſame place alſo: <hi>Epiſcopi ab Apostolis instituti in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſijs &amp; Succeſſores eorum vſque ad nos. Biſhops ordayned by the Apostles in the Churches, and their Succeſſors vntill our times.</hi> Where alſo the Romane Biſhops <hi>Anicetus, Pius, Hyginus,</hi> he nameth <hi>Presbyters.</hi> By all which it is evident, that the name <hi>Biſhop</hi> &amp; <hi>Preſbyter</hi> was not yet exactly diſtinguiſhed as after it was, but remayned yet (as it were) common and indifferent to all Miniſters of the word, even ſo as it was vſed by the Apoſtles in their writings. Alſo it appeareth heereby that there was not then any kind of Dioceſan Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops. For the name then ought to haue ben very diſtinct, and peculiar to him, as afterward it came to paſſe. Much leſſe had any Biſhop a power to rule over a whole Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe. Otherwiſe <hi>Ireneus</hi> ſhould not haue vſed theſe names and termes then ſo indifferently.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertullians</hi> teſtimony alſo ſeemeth very agreable in this <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> point. Where ſpeaking of Chriſtians ordinary Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations in Cities in his time he ſaith <hi>Corpus ſumus, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pertulian. Apolog. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note> we are all one Body, &amp;c. And againe <hi>Coimus in Cetum &amp; ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationem, &amp;c.</hi> We all com togeather into a Company and Congregation. He ſaith not plurally <hi>in cetus &amp; aggre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gationes</hi> into divers Companies &amp; Congregations; as ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it ſeemeth he ſhould and would haue ſaid, if there had ben then in one Citie many ordinary conſtant Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations. Specially ſeeing he ſaith alſo of the ſame ſingular Congregation: <hi>Ibidem (est) Cenſura divina: iudicatur magno cum pondere, &amp;c. There are divine Cenſures exerciſed. The iudgement is given with great waight, &amp;c.</hi> Which ſurely was done in every ſuch conſtant Congregation as before he ſpake of. And yet but in one ſingular Congregation &amp; not in many, nor in one over many conſtantly appointed in one Citie at that time.</p>
            <pb n="61" facs="tcp:21672:35"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Euſebius</hi> Hiſtory ſheweth that the Churches of the moſt <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> famous Cities were each of them primitiuely no more but a <hi>Pariſh</hi> only; that is, but one ordinary conſtant Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation only. As wehre he nameth the Church of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem<note n="a" place="margin">Euſe. lib. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>the Pariſh of Ieruſalem,</hi> of Epheſus <hi>the Pariſh of</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Lib. 3.28.</note> 
               <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus,</hi> and ſo of<note n="c" place="margin">Lib. 3.13.18. lib. 4.1.4.5.19.</note> 
               <hi>Alexandria,</hi> of<note n="d" place="margin">Lib. 3.32</note> 
               <hi>Hierapolis,</hi> of<note n="e" place="margin">Lib. 4.22</note> 
               <hi>Corinth,</hi> of<note n="f" place="margin">Lib 4.25.</note> 
               <hi>Sardis,</hi> of<note n="g" place="margin">Lib. 5.5.</note> 
               <hi>Lyons,</hi> &amp; divers Churches <hi>the</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Lib. 4.22 6.</note> 
               <hi>Pariſhes of Crete.</hi> He no where mentioneth many Churches nor Pariſhes vnder one Biſhop in any Citie till Iulianus time in Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, as before we obſerved.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Epiphanius</hi> teſtimonie alſo our Aſſertion is maintai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Who ſaith Primitiuely<note n="*" place="margin">Epiph co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tr. Ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>. 73.</note> 
               <hi>in a ſmall Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation a Biſhop</hi> was ordayned <hi>alone</hi> without other Preſbyters aſſiſting him. And in ſom places <hi>only Preſbyters and Deacons without a Biſhop.</hi> In other places, that is in great &amp; populous Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s <hi>where they had meete men</hi> to be choſen, there they choſe in each of them a Biſhop with other aſſiſtant Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters. By which it appeareth conſequently that every<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where a Biſhop then was but of one particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation only whether greater or ſimaller.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="proof" n="2"/>
            <p>
               <label>The ſecond part is proved.</label>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations had their owne go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment Ecclefiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call. Ignat. ad Philad.</note>NEither let any imagine that theſe particular Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations then wanted their owne Eccleſiaſticall go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment among themſelves only. It is moſt evident that they had it &amp; exerciſed it only within themſelues ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily. Which is plaine by that of <hi>Ignatius</hi> writing to one of them thus: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>It is meet for you as being the Church of God to choſe by common co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent your Biſhop.</hi> And to an other particular Church thus,<note n="*" place="margin">Ad Smyrna.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>In the Church (which is with you at Smyrna) there is not any thing aboue the Biſhop.</hi> He meaneth the Biſhop or Paſtor of the particular Congregation is of
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:21672:36"/>greateſt authoritie and aboue any other there whomſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. So that they in that Congregation had all governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſimply and ſolely among themſelves. He ſpeaketh heere of governing <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Spiritually,</hi> not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Civilly.</hi> For thus the Magiſtrate is Supreme both in and over each Church and whatſoever Church matters, as Mai. <hi>Beza</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly and dutifully<note n="*" place="margin">Theod. Bez. de Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com. &amp; Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſbyt.</note> ſpeaketh, &amp; we<note n="†" place="margin">Pag. 57.</note> before obſerved. Yea verily thus the Magiſtrat is ſupreme whether he care for the Church, or care not. Hence therfore we conclude, that theſe particular Churches had the ordinary Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall government of themſelves among themſelves. <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> alſo in the place before cited ſheweth ſo much, ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of each particular ordinarie Congregation in his dayes: <hi>Ibidem (est) cenſura divina. Iudicatur magno cum pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere vt apud certos de Dei conſpectu.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.39.</note> 
               <hi>Preſident probati quique Seniores. There are divine Cenſures. They iudge with great waight and adviſednes, as being ſure that God ſeeth them. The ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved Elders are the chiefe, or do governe theſe Cenſures.</hi> Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all particular ordinary Congregations inioyed their owne ſpirituall governement then in thoſe times. There is no ſuſpicion of any reſtraint or abridging of them ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in till <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the 13. Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Anno 260.</note> at the ſooneſt.</p>
            <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="proof" n="3"/>
            <p>
               <label>The third part is proved.</label>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">No Maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of rule, but only Prioritie of order in a primitive Biſhop.</note>BEſides the teſtimonies before alleaged, <hi>Ambroſe</hi> in plain wordes telleth vs this, that primitively<note n="*" place="margin">Ambro in Eph. 4. &amp; 1 Tim. 3.</note> 
               <hi>A Biſhop</hi> was no more but <hi>primus</hi> Presbyter, <hi>the foremost in order</hi> among the other Miniſters of the word in the Synods, or where there were other in the ſame Congregation with him. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> the Biſhop then differed not in Maioritie of rule from any other Paſtor. And therefore then there was no Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan Church vſing governement, nor Dioceſan Biſhop ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling other Paſtors and Churches. Much leſſe was there
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:21672:36"/>any Dioceſan Lord Biſhop then.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ierome</hi> doth likewiſe: Where he ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Ierom. ad Evagr. &amp; in Tit. 1.</note> 
               <hi>A Biſhop and</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="8"/> 
               <hi>an Elder</hi> or common Paſtor, <hi>by Divine institution and ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, are all one.</hi> And <hi>Maioritie</hi> among them came in <hi>by the custome of the Church and Humane diſpoſition.</hi> He meaneth Maioritie of Ruling, becauſe he ſheweth heere that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly all did rule<note n="“" place="margin">in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>muni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>or</hi> communi Preſbytero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum conſili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>in common.</hi> Wherefore by his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there was not at the firſt any Maioritie of rule in a Biſhop over Paſtors. Much leſſe were there any Dioceſan L. Biſhops ruling by their ſole authoritie in thoſe times. Som Prioritie in order, we doubt not, was alwayes: Firſt Pariſhionall, and then Dioceſan ſom good while after, as before is ſhewed. Yea the Pariſhionall prioritie of order was (we deny not) conſtant, yea even among Paſtors who had otherwiſe all one Office intirely. I ſay, this was where there were divers Miniſters of the word in one par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregation. As we doubt not there were in ſom places. Now for this matter, viz. Biſhops Maioritie in governement above Preſbyters, and alſo concerning <hi>Ieromes</hi> opinion thereof, it is not amiſſe to obſerve what D. <hi>Bilſon</hi> alſo hath taught and avouched. In his<note n="*" place="margin">Againſt the Semina. part. 2. pag. 318.</note> Firſt Booke he ſayeth, It was not <hi>by the institution of Christ, nor his Apoſtles,</hi> but long after <hi>by the conſent of the Churches, the Custom of the tymes, and the will of Princes.</hi> Where alſo he ſheweth that this was <hi>Ieromes</hi> iudgement likewiſe. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſince (I can not tell how, nor why) <hi>D. Bilſon</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Perpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. gov. pag. 236.237.238.</note> chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged much his minde heerein: and yet with no more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crepance from himſelfe then from the trueth, and from al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all learned men beſide both ancient and later.</p>
            <p>Further, this reaſon prooveth the preſent whole Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi rend="margQuotes">If the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> vſed religiouſly for a Church <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="9"/> Viſible with order and governement, do and ought to
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:21672:37"/>keepe in all good Authors a iuſt proportion anſwerable to the Civill and Originall vſe thereof, then it muſt needs be in proper ſignification a particular Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation only.</hi> For Originally and Civilly in all Greeke Authors <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth one particular Aſſembly in one place only, as an Aſſembly of the people at <hi>Athens,</hi> in <hi>Epheſus,</hi> in <hi>Corinth, &amp;c</hi> being com togeather in their publike iudgement-place. Which is evident by the writinges of <hi>Plato, Demosthenes, Iſocrates, Xenophon, &amp;c.</hi> Yea in the<note n="*" place="margin">Acte 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.39.40.</note> Actes of the Apoſtles we do finde it likewiſe ſo vſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">But the Apoſtles and other Eccleſiaſticall writers for 200. yeares after Chriſt vſing this worde for a Viſible Church with order and governement do ſpeak properly, and ſo ought to keepe a iuſt proportion in it anſwerable to the Civill and originall vſe thereof.</hi> This ſentence is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly true and vndenyable. If any think he can ſhew to the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rie, let it be ſhewed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore the Apoſtles and other Eccleſiaſticall Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for 200. yeares ſpace after Chriſt vſing this word for a Viſib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Church with order and governement, do ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie by it a particular Congregation only. And it no where ſignifieth in them a Dioceſan Church, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where note that the ſtrength of this reaſon ſtandeth wholy in the proper taking and vſing of this word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Church.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Note.</note> The Adverſaries error hath advantage by the improper and ambiguous vſe of it: which is Sophiſticall. Yea if you will, their ſenſe is a<note n="“" place="margin">By the Scriptures verdict.</note> falſe ſenſe of it; wherein yet it often vſed in Writers and in common ſpeach for want of due regard. By which meanes alſo ſundry other errors have crept in heeretofore &amp; much prevayled, even by miſ-vnderſtanding of certayne wordes. As we may ſee
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:21672:37"/>in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: and in Latin <hi>Meritum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Equivocall wordes.</note> 
               <hi>Poenitentia, Crux, Sacramentum, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of all thoſe Teſtimonies before alleadged, this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall reaſon may be concluded. <hi rend="margQuotes">No Dioceſan Church <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="10"/> or Biſhop was knowen or once heard of in the world, till many diſtinct ordinary Congregations began to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed in one Citie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">But there was no Multiplication nor diſtinction of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ordinarie and conſtant Congregations in a Citie, till about 200. yeares after Chriſt.</hi> Som co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iecture, it was long after this. No man ſheweth that it was before this. The truth in deed heereof, that for this while generally in each Citie there was but one ordinary conſtant Congregation of Chriſtians, hath ben plentifully ſhewed in the Proofes of this 2. Aſſertion before going.</p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore till about 200. yeares after Chriſt there was no manner of Dioceſan Church or Biſhop knowen, nor once heard of in all the Chriſtian world. No not the Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan Titular Biſhop: much leſſe any Dioceſan ruling Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where yet we deny not but that one particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation or Church being populous might occaſionally and vncertainly in the time of perſecution for their ſafetie ſake aſſemble in divers ſmaller Meetings.<note place="margin">As before we noted pag. 19.20.</note> As alſo they did we doubt not, many times within the ſpace of theſe 200. yeares after Chriſt. Howbeit yet theſe ſmaller Meetings were not ſo many Churches properly: becauſe they were not ordinary ſett Companies, nor conſtantly diſtinct So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, as Churches ought to be, and as our Pariſhes now are. Thoſe divers Occaſionall and vncertaine meetings made but one Church and ordinary Congregation,<note place="margin">Act. 6, 1.</note> yea though the whole nomber were too populous for one
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:21672:38"/>actual Aſſembly ordinarily. It is true in ſuch caſe they ought to diſtinguiſh and diſtribut themſelves into divers competent ſet Congregations which ſhould be ſo many proper and intire Churches. But when they are (as they were in thoſe primitive times) dayly in great perill of cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell perſecution, they may with reaſon remaine ſomwhile vndiſtinguiſhed, &amp; not ſo diſtribute themſelves, which in time of peace and ſafetie they always ought to do. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in now ſom Reformed Churches beyond Seas do ſeeme to offend.</p>
            <p>If any ſay the troubleſomnes of thoſe times or the yong age of the Churches who were not yet growen vp to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, cauſed that there were no Dioceſan Churches with governement nor Dioceſan ruling Biſhops then. And we take advantage of the ſpecial ſtate of thoſe times, vrging it to our purpoſe generally.</p>
            <p>I anſwer; we vrge from the ſtate and order of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike primitive Churches nothing but what is generall in them, and ought to be perpetuall with vs. So that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the troubleſomnes of thoſe times, nor the young age of the Churches then do give vs our advantage. For not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding theſe ſpeciall Circumſtances the Viſible Churches vſing gouernement and the Biſhops then, might have ben very well Dioceſan and Provinciall, if Chriſt had ſo inſtituted and the Apoſtles had ſo framed and left them. Nothing in the world hindereth but they might eaſily have ben ſuch even in thoſe times. But the world knew none ſuch then, as I have ſaid. And it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pietie to ſay Chriſtes Churches were vnperfect then, as touching their Viſible forme &amp; conſtitution, their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery, and the whole lawfull order of worſhipping God in them. Or that the times ſince have made them more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:21672:38"/>then they were as the Apoſtles left them. Wherefore this advantage do we ſtand vpon, and this do we vrge, viz. the ſame patterne and forme of Viſible Churches vſing governement that was then vniverſally practiſed &amp; recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved immediatly from Chriſt and the Apoſtles; which was <hi>Pariſhionall</hi> not <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> as hath ben declared.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="assertion">
            <head>The 3. Aſſertion.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The Scriptures of the New Testament do containe &amp; ſet forth vnto vs (beſides the governement by Extraordinarie Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Apostles Prophets Evangelistes) an ordinarie forme of Church-governement vſed then.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">IF in the New Teſtament one kinde of a Viſible Church vſing governement and no other is to be found,<note place="margin">1. Reaſon</note> alſo if ſpeciall diſtinct ordinarie Offices for Church-governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſpeciall Actions therevnto belonging, be ſett downe therein; then the Scripture contayneth a ſpeciall forme of Church-government which was ordinary then.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">But in the New Teſtament<note n="a" place="margin">See be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 1. Aſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion 2. Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</note> One kinde of a Viſible Church vſing governement (namely a particular ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Congregation) and no other is found: alſo ſpeciall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct ordinarie Offices for Church-governement are ſet downe therein, as Pariſhionall<note n="b" place="margin">Tit 1.5, 7 1 Tim. 3.1, 2. Ephe. 4.11. Phil. 1.1. Act. 20.28 1 Pet. 5.2. Act. 14.23</note> 
                  <hi>Biſhops</hi> or <hi>Pastors,</hi> and an other ſort of (not Lay but Eccleſiaſticall)<note n="c" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.17. compa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>red with Gal. 6.10. &amp; 1 Tim. 4.10. Rom. 12.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1 Cor. 12.28. Iam. 5.14 Adde the ancient Writers: Ignat. Epiſt. ad Trall. Tarſ, &amp; Smyr. Tertull. Apol. c. 39. &amp; d Baptiſme. Ambr. in 1. Tim. 5, &amp; in 1. Cor. 12.28, Ierom. in Iſa. 3. Auguſt. Epiſt, 137.</note> 
                  <hi>Elders,</hi> who by their Ordinary office were only to aſſiſt in governement. Third: the ſpecial Actions belonging to Church-govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are alſo ſet downe in the Scripture; as <hi>Election</hi> of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:21672:39"/>
                  <hi>Excommunication</hi> of ſpirituall offendors, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">Therfore the Scripture of the New Teſtament co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayneth a ſpeciall forme of Church-governement ordinary then.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Where it is to be noted, that in thoſe firſt times there were alſo thoſe other Officers in the Churches:<note place="margin">Note.</note> 
               <hi>Apostles Evangelistes</hi> and <hi>Prophetes.</hi> But they had Calling and giftes immediatly from God; the others Calling was alwayes by men. They abode not in one Church, as the other did. Their government and vſe was not perpetuall but tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rary and extraordinarie. They therefore hindered not the other, neither can they now hinder: The rather ſith they do not now remaine, but are ceaſed.</p>
            <p>Alſo, thoſe <hi>Pariſhionall Biſhops</hi> and thoſe other <hi>Elders</hi> aſſiſting in government,<note place="margin">Note.</note> did differ in their Ordinary office. Yea though they both did ſomtimes Preach, &amp;c: yet thus they differed notwithſtanding. But a Pariſhionall Biſhop or Paſtor cannot differ in his ordinary office of Preaching, &amp;c. from an Elder who is alſo by ordinary office a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, &amp;c. Therefore he is heere an other Church Elder, viz. by ordinary office no Preacher, but only a helper in governement, who in thoſe forenoted places is ſpoken of, and differeth in his ordinary office plainly from every Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop or Paſtor.</p>
            <p>Yet ſom obiect vehemently, that all Elders in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Churches who aſſiſted the Biſhop in government<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> were very Paſtors: ſeeing they had power to preach the word, &amp;c. And that thoſe mentioned namely in <hi>Ignatius</hi> and <hi>Tertullian.</hi> before alleaged, were only ſuch. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then there were none ſuch only governing Elders at all, as we conceave.</p>
            <p>I anſwer, That they differed even then in their ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie office from Paſtors it is cleere and queſtionles (not only
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:21672:39"/>in thoſe fore-alleaged places of Scripture, but alſo) in the foreſaid ancient writers <hi>Ignatius,</hi> and <hi>Tertullian,</hi> &amp;c. Yet for more evidence to this point which ſom labour mightily to obſcure and darken, I affirme that <hi>Preaching</hi> and <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preting</hi> Gods word is of 3. ſortes in the Scripture,<note place="margin">Preaching of 3. ſortes.</note> and ſo it was vſed in the firſt Churches after.<note n="1" place="margin">1.</note> We read of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching which was by<note n="*" place="margin">Rom. 10.14, 15.</note> ordinary office. This, we ſay, the Paſtors &amp; Teachers only did perform.<note n="2" place="margin">2.</note> That which was for exerciſe and for trayning vp, for the making of ſom apt and able for the Miniſterie of the word, yea and for a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther increaſe of giftes even in the Miniſterie themſelves. This was the exerciſe of Propheſie or Interpretatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the<note n="“" place="margin">1 Cor. 14 29. 1 Cor. 12.30.</note> Scripture calleth it. Wherein were receaved ſom<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 14 1.24, 31.</note> Lay men, namely by the Churches order. And then ſo like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe might the Deacons, &amp; Elders alſo ſomtimes Preach, though they were no Preachers by office. Nevertheleſſe yet we acknowledge the Preachers were and ought to be the chiefe heerein. But the<note n="3" place="margin">3.</note> ſort of Preaching is moſt of all heere to be marked. Third. vpon occaſion (in Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches without order and ſcattered, and alſo vnto perſons who were not yet gathered to any Church) there was Preaching which was generall and common for<note n="*" place="margin">Acts 11.19.</note> all true Chriſtians lively Members of Chriſt, indued with giftes of knowledge &amp; ſound iudgement in Religion. In which ſenſe <hi>Ambroſe</hi> is to be vnderſtood,<note place="margin">Ambro. in Ephe. 4.</note> where he ſaith that in the firſt times every Chriſtian preached the worde. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it now a fault but a ſingular vertue for godly Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders to inſtruct in the word of God their owne chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and ſervantes. Howbeit in Churches orderly gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and ſetled, no privat Chriſtian may preſume, neither did any then preſume publikely to preach or interpret the word, except for ſom ſpeciall reaſon he were ſpecially ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:21672:40"/>ſo to do by the lawful Governors of the Church. And ſo did ſom preach publikely, yea in the very Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches after the Apoſtles, being even but Lay men as <hi>Ignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> do witnes in the foreſaid places. Where they ſhew, that alſo the Deacons did and might preach af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this maner. And alſo that the Elders which were ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narie Aſſiſtantes in governement, did and might preach thus likewiſe. I ſay ſtill, after this 3. manner; that is like as the very Lay men did, and as the Deacons did; that is not by their ordinary office, but by the Paſtors and Biſhops ſpeciall appointment to them all. Wherefore this proveth not the Elders there ſpoken of to be Preachers by Office: nay it proveth plainly the contrarie, that by their ordinary office they were not Preachers, but only governing El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. And this is the purpoſe that we alleage them for.</p>
            <p>Finally we may obſerve that ſom ſhadow of them ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſtill to remayne, though greatly corrupted, in the <hi>Church Wardens</hi> of our Pariſhes. Yea ſom ſuch depravatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and degencration in them was begun (we doubt not) in <hi>Ambroſe, Ierome,</hi> and <hi>Austines</hi> time: although yet the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient trueth appeareth well enough thereby notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="assertion">
            <head>The 4. Aſſertion.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>The ordinary forme of Church governement ſet foorth vnto vs in the New Testament, ought to be kept ſtill by vs: it is not changeable by men, and therefore it only is lawfull.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">IF the ordinary forme of Church-government ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God in his word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Reaſon</note> 
               <hi>was never ſince repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:21672:40"/>by himſelfe, then</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Mat. 28.20. 2 Theſ. 2.15. 1. Tim. 6.14.</note>
               <hi> the ſame remayneth ſtill appointed for vs; it is ſtill neceſſary, and is not changeable by men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">But the ordinary forme of Church-governement ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by God in his word, and ſpecified before in our 3. Aſſertio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, was never ſince repealed nor cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged by himſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore the ſame remaineth ſtill appointed by God for vs, it is now ſtil neceſſarie, &amp; is not cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geable by any men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">If every lawfull Viſible Church vſing governement, &amp; alſo if every lawfull Church-Office, and Action,<note place="margin">2. Reaſon</note> ought to be particularly allowed by God in his word, then the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie forme of Church-governement ſet forth vnto vs in the new Teſtament, is neceſſary for vs now ſtill, it is vn. changeable and only lawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">But every lawfull Viſible Church vſing governement, and alſo every lawfull Church Office, and Action<note n="*" place="margin">1. Aſſert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 1. Reaſon. Heb. 5.4. Mat. 21.25. 1 Cor. 12.5 28. Ephe. 4.11, 12, 13. 1 Tim. 2.5 Ioh. 10.1.</note> ought to be particularly (as touching the kinde thereof) allowed in Gods worde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi rend="margQuotes">Therefore the Ordinarie forme of Church-governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſet downe vnto vs in the New Teſtament, is neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie for vs now ſtill, it is vnchangeable and only lawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heerevnto (for a concluſion) let vs adde certaine lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned mens very cleere Teſtimonies, which perſons yet are no way partiall for vs. <hi>Doctor Bilſon</hi> (who is now Lord Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Wincheſter) ſaith thus:<note n="“" place="margin">D. Bilſon perpet goy. pag. 3.</note> 
               <hi>We must not frame what kinde of Regiment we list for the Ministers of Christes Church, but rather obſerve and marke what maner of externall governe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the Lord hath best liked and allowed in his Church even from the beginning.</hi> And,<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 19.</note> 
               <hi>It is certaine we must not chooſe out the corruptions of time nor inventions of men, but aſcend to the originall ordinance of God, and thence derive our platforme of Church-governement.</hi> To do otherwiſe, is <hi>To tranſgreſſe the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:21672:41"/>commandement of God for the traditions of men.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 49.</note> 
               <hi>The Apostles had their mouthes and pennes directed and guyded by the Holy Ghost into all trueth aſwell of doctrine as Diſcipline.</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles<note n="“" place="margin">Pag. 43.</note> 
               <hi>ſet an order amongst Christians in all things needfull for the governement, continuance, peace, and vnitie af the Church.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 221.</note> 
               <hi>What authoritie had others after the Apostles deathes to change the Apostolike governement?</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Pag 111.</note> 
               <hi>They that have authority in the Church muſt looke not only what they challenge but alſo fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom they derive it: If from the Apoſtles, then are they their Succeſſors: If from Chriſt as colleagues ioyned with the Apoſtles, we muſt find that conſociation in the Goſpell, before we cleere them from intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. No man ſhould take this honor vnto himſelfe but he that is called of God as the Apoſtles were. If they be called by Chriſt, read their aſsignation from Chriſt: if they be not, ſurceaſe that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 339.</note> 
               <hi>If the name</hi> [of Dioceſan Biſhop] <hi>were new and lately invented by men, the loſſe thereof were not great: yea retay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the name they muſt be knowen to be of men and not of God.</hi> Heerevnto accordeth <hi>D. Sutcliffe</hi> in his booke intituled <hi>O. E.</hi> againſt <hi>N. D.</hi> where he refuting the calling of the Ieſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ites, ſaith thus:<note n="“" place="margin">D. Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>liffe, or O. K. againſt N. D. pag. 110.</note> 
               <hi>It is not enough to ſay that they have a rule and learning, and live orderly but they muſt have their Office and calling allowed by Chriſt Ieſus, if they meane to take vpon them the office of Paſtors Teachers and Governors in Chriſtes Church. Wherefore either let them ſhew themſelves to have a lawfull cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or let them not thinke much to be thruſt out as intruders. We doe not find either in the Epiſtle to the Epheſians, chap 4. or the firſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians, chapt. 12. any ſuch extravagant Friars.</hi> Thus do both theſe learned men (and our no great friends) maintaine with vs ſingularly <hi>The Scriptures perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> even in theſe outward Eccleſiaſtical matters. Yea fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſidering the Scriptures phraſe &amp; maner of ſpeach perpetually ſignifying that there is not only One Viſible
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:21672:41"/>Church of Chriſt properly, but Many in number in the world; nor only one in a Nation or Province, but many, as before<note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 19. 20.</note> we have declared: therefore one of theſe (viz. the B. of Wint.) is to be well obſerved how he avoucheth the holy Scriptures perfection alſo even for the phraſe and maner of ſpeach, and how vnlawfull a thing he holdeth it to be to vſe any<note n="†" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> new wordes (for religious matters) other the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the very Scripture vſeth. Thus generally he affirmeth, though he applieth it to another point the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> now we ſpeak of. Saith he<note n="“" place="margin">The full redemption of man by &amp;c. Pag. 41.</note> 
               <hi>What I reade in the word of God that I beleeve, what I do not reade that I do not beleeve. In Gods cauſes we may not eaſily leave Gods wordes, and with a new kinde of ſpeach make way for a new kind of faith. We must learne from God what to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve, &amp; not by correcting or inverting his words teach him how to ſpeake.</hi> This religious ſtrictnes even touching the words of Scripture, is indeed (I graunt) to be held religiouſly and perpetually, vnderſtanding the words to be ſuch as either the Scripture it ſelfe vſeth, or may be neceſſarie conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence be proved and allowed from the very Scripture.</p>
            <p>But now how vniuſtly are we vſed by them, yea how vnchriſtianly, when toward vs they will ſtand to nothing of all this: and yet (forſooth) all muſt go ſtill on their ſide. The very Papiſtes do ſee and acknowledge this that I ſay; viz. both that theſe grounds of the Scriptures abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lut perfection in all Eccleſiaſticall matters (whereon we exactly do ſtand) are the true and right principles of the <hi>Protestants</hi> Religion, &amp; alſo that the Dioceſan L. Biſhops,<note place="margin">The only true Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</note> do, and muſt needes turne away from theſe principles, &amp; deny them when they deale with vs: and muſt ioyn plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie with the Catholikes in their anſwers, if they will main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine themſelves. Thus ſay they, when one obiected that<note n="*" place="margin">Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ves from Spaine &amp; Holland</note> 
               <hi>The Puritans</hi> (as they falſely and maliciouſlie call vs)
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:21672:42"/>
               <hi>would certainly be extinguiſhed if the Queene ſhould live any nomber of yeares. Tuſh</hi> ſaith an other, <hi>you are deceaved. Nay much more poſsible and likely it is, that the Puritan ſhall over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>com the Protestant, then the contrarie. For that the Puritan buildeth directly vpon the Protestants first grounds in Religion, and deduceth thereof cleerely and by ordinary conſequence all his concluſions. Which the Protestant can not deny by Divinity but only by Policie and humane ordination, or by turning</hi>
               <note n="“" place="margin">The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes Supplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion An. 1604 hath the like. pag. 17.</note> 
               <hi>to Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like anſwers contrary to their owne principles. And it is hard for any man ſincerely to be a Proteſtant, but that he will eaſily paſſe alſo on (more or leſſe) to be a Puritan. And only they in effect will be against them, who are intereſſed in the other ſide (as Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, Biſhops, Archdeacons, Canons, Notaries, Registers, Civill Lawyers, and the like) for not leeſing their Commodities, &amp;c.</hi> This do the very Papiſtes diſcerne and confeſſe. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withall they propheſie alſo (as it were) if the Proteſtants Religion be not rooted out, that the Puritanes profeſſion will finally prevaile both againſt the common Proteſtants and the Catholiks alſo. Which ſom with vs much fearing and vngraciouſly ſtriving againſt, when they could not endure<note n="*" place="margin">Scottizing &amp; Geneva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcipline, pa. 31.</note> 
               <hi>our hope of one Darius</hi> comming to build vp the Temple of God among vs, they made it no leſſe then a Treaſonable mind in vs when we could not conceale in deed ſuch a hope that we had long agoe of this Princes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-comming. Wherefore alſo they maintayned Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie Prieſtes (very Traitors in deed) publikly to taxe this our moſt Chriſtian &amp; Noble <hi>Darius</hi> (whom God hath of his ſingular mercy now ſent vnto vs) as a Puritan King, ſaying:<note n="“" place="margin">Quodli. pag. 26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>The Puritans have Princes none at all (vnleſſe it be one) on their ſide.</hi> Their malice was thus mooved, becauſe they were not ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the Kings moſt holy &amp; religious <hi>Confeſsion of his faith</hi> made long ſince and publiſhed to the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:21672:42"/>view of the world, as no other Kinge in Chriſtendom hath don, and altogeather agreeable to our Profeſſion. Where<note n="*" place="margin">Confeſſ. of faith At Edingburg. Ann. 1580.</note> 
               <hi>he detesteth all Rites, Signes, and Traditions brought into the Church without or against the word of God. Promiſing and ſwearing by the great Name of our Lord to continue in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience of the doctrine and diſcipline of the Church</hi> (that is in Scotland) <hi>and ſhall defend the ſame according to his vocation and power all the dayes of his life.</hi> Which alſo of late againe he hath in effect renued and confirmed: and that even then when there was doubt how his future ſubiects in En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland would entertaine his comming. Thus lately wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth our worthy &amp; gracious King admoniſhing his Sonne the noble Prince<note n="“" place="margin">Baſilicon dôro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. pag. 43.</note> 
               <hi>The doctrine and diſcipline preſerve in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie according to Gods word.</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Pag 7.</note> 
               <hi>The whole Scripture is dited by Gods Spirit, thereby, as by his lively word to instruct and rule the whole Church Militant to the end of the world.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 6.</note> 
               <hi>The firſt part of mans ſervice to his God which is Religion, that is the worſhip of God according to his revealed will, it is wholy grounded vpon the Scripture.</hi>
               <note n="“" place="margin">Pag. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Frame all your affections to follow preciſely the rule there ſet downe.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Pag. 15, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>By Superſtition I meane when one reſtraines himſelfe to any other rule in the ſervice of God then is warranted by the word the only true ſquare of Gods ſervice.</hi> The forme e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in Scotland is<note n="“" place="margin">To the Reader.</note> 
               <hi>the only true forme of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</hi> which we vnderſtand as ſpoken in this reſpect that they profeſſe to renounce all humane Traditions therein. For theſe thinges have thoſe evill Beaſtes maliciouſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proched his Maieſtie, as if this were worthy of no better name then a <hi>Puritan</hi> opinion. In deed for this only opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thus they have, and do ſtill revile vs. But we commit the iudgement heereof to the Lord. Wherefore final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie let vs obſerve heere (in regard of the premiſſes) that godly, wiſe, and neceſſarie counſell of <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> a man
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:21672:43"/>of worthy memory. Saith he,<note n="*" place="margin">Martyr Epiſt. ad Dom. Polo.</note> 
               <hi>Conſulo praeterea vt Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plinam quanto ocyùs fieri poterit in vestras Eccleſias omninò in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vehatis, &amp;c. I counſaill you moreover that as ſoone as poſsible may be, you bring in the Diſcipline wholy into your Churches. For if it be not receaved at the beginning when men are whot in love with the Goſpell, it will not be eaſily lett in afterward when ſom coldnes ſhall creepe in, as vſually it commeth to paſſe. And how vainely men labour without it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">England deſcribed.</note> 
               <hi>very many Churches may be an example vnto you: which from the foundations of their reſtoring when they would not vndergo ſo healthfull a yoke, they could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver after in their life and maners be brought into order by any rule. Whence it is (with grief I ſpeake it) that all thinges almost have little firmenes and do threaten ruine on every ſide. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a grievous dammage, and a certayne deſtruction of the Churches, if the ſinew of diſcipline be wanting vnto them. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may they be ſaid truly and ſoundly to have and profeſſe the Goſpell which either want the Diſcipline, or deſpiſe it, or have no deſire of it. Surely ſeeing it is delivered vs with ſo great diligence in the Goſpells and Apoſtles Epiſtles, we muſt confeſſe it to be not the leaſt part of Chriſtian Religion. Whereby it commeth to paſſe that the Goſpell ſeemeth to be neglected by them, who do put away from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo excellent a part thereof: &amp;c.</hi> Thus ſay theſe lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men.</p>
            <p>Howbeit yet our Adverſaries do &amp; will accuſe vs that we are <hi>Schiſmatikes</hi> and <hi>Seditious</hi> in refuſing the Dioceſan Biſhops authoritie and rule Eccleſiaſticall, which is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blikely receaved.</p>
            <p>But we anſwer; It is no ſedition nor diſloyaltie at all, it is no miſbehaviour againſt the King, dutifully to endevour that thoſe partes of Chriſtes Goſpell, which yet are wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, ſhould be entertayned among vs; that Chriſtes true Viſible Churches ſhould be acknowledged and regarded
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:21672:43"/>as by Gods word they ought to be, &amp; that in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſts owne ſpirituall ordinances (and none other) ſhould be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed. Nay, it were diſloyaltie againſt the King and his eſtate to endevour otherwiſe. Againe touching Schiſme,
<list>
                  <item>1. We affirme (with the Canoniſtes) <hi>Non ſeparatio ſed cauſa facit Schiſmaticum: Not ſeparation, but the cauſe ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth a Schiſmatike.</hi> Wherefore it behoveth all wiſe men to ſee where the cauſe is.</item>
                  <item>2. Then we affirme &amp; proove that our adverſaries themſelves do cauſe or make the Schiſme, which in deed is amongſt vs.</item>
               </list>
For the Apoſtle ſaith, They make Schiſmes who teach [any thing Eccleſiaſtical]<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Rom. 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide</hi> the doctrine which the Apoſtles left vs, &amp; they ought to be avoyded. Now our Adverſaries do teach and vrge all their forenoted Traditions moſt evidently <hi>beſides</hi> the Apoſtles doctrine and ordinances. Yea verily <hi>contrary</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, as before we have ſhewed. Whereby it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt who are in deed the Schiſmaticks, and to be refuſed. To which purpoſe alſo <hi>Cyprian</hi> witneſſeth, ſaying:<note n="“" place="margin">Cypr. de Lapſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Non Eccleſiae iungitur qui ab Evangelio ſeparatur. He that differeth from the Goſpell ioyneth not to the Church: but ſchiſmeth from it.</hi> And <hi>Augustin,</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Aug. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Peril. 2.25.</note> 
               <hi>Vtrum Schiſmatici nos ſumus an vos, nec ego nec tu ſed Christus interrogetur, vt indicet Eccleſiam ſuam. Lege ergo Evangelium &amp; reſpondet tibi, &amp;c. Whether we or you be Schiſmatickes aske not me, nor your ſelves, but aske Christ that be may ſhew his owne Church. Read the Goſpell therefore and it anſwereth thee, &amp;c.</hi> Againe,<note n="*" place="margin">De Vnit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Eccle cap. 3</note> 
               <hi>Ibi quaeramus Eccleſiam, ibi di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcutiamus cauſam nostram. Nolo humanis documentis ſed divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis oraculis ſanctam Eccleſiam demonſtrari.</hi>
               <note n="“" place="margin">Contr. Creſcon. Gram. 1.33</note> 
               <hi>Eccleſiam ſine vlla ambiguitate ſancta ſcriptura demonſtrat. There</hi> [in the New Teſtament] <hi>let vs ſeeke the Church. There let vs examine our cauſe. I cannot abide that the holy Church ſhould be ſhewed by mens doctrines, but by the Divine Oracles. The holy Scriptures
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:21672:44"/>do demonſtrat the Church without any doubt.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Chryſoſt. operis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect. Hom <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3.</note> 
               <hi>Eccleſia cogn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcitur tantummodò per Scripturas. Onely by the Scriptures is the Church knowen.</hi> And another ſaith:<note n="†" place="margin">Baſil de confeſ. ſid.</note> 
               <hi>Manifesta <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>à Fide, &amp; Superbiae crimen aut reprobare quid exijs quae ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ripta ſunt, aut aliquid ſuperinducere ex non ſcriptis. It is a manifest falling away from the faith, &amp; a ſinne of pride, either to refuſe any thing of that which is written, or to bring in any thing beſides that which is written.</hi> Againe <hi>Cyprian</hi> ſaith,<note n="*" place="margin">Cypr. epi. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>No other thing ought to be don of vs then that which our Lord for vs hath don before vs.</hi>
               <note n="“" place="margin">Epiſt. 1.7</note> 
               <hi>Whoſoever gathereth from any other ground, he ſcattereth. It is adulterous, it is impious, it is ſacrilegious whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver it be, which mad men do inſtitute violating thereby the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine or dinance.</hi> And againe,<note n="†" place="margin">Ad Pomp.</note> 
               <hi>Vnde eſt iſta Traditio? Whence commeth this Tradion,</hi> (ſpeaking namely of an outward Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall cuſtom) <hi>Whether is it from the Lords authoritie in the Goſpells, or from the Apoſtles preceptes and Epiſtles?</hi> Where his meaning in brief is, that every ſuch (that is Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call) Vnwritten Tradition whatſoever, ought to be vtterly reiected.</p>
            <p>Theſe Reaſons I had, Chriſtian Reader, which long ſince perſwaded me in this cauſe. Wherfore I was moved in conſcience to communicate them to Gods people now in this ſeaſonable and neceſſary time. Conſidering that theſe things are farre from matters indifferent or arbitra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, but are in deed very greatly importing the common ſalvation. Beſides we have ben often &amp; vehemently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked therevnto. And the preſent opportunitie exacteth it at our handes, as all men do vnderſtand. To God only wiſe be praiſe through Ieſus Chriſt for ever, <hi>Rom. 16.27.</hi>
            </p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Via vna, cor vnum.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:21672:44"/>
            <head>AN EXHORTATION.</head>
            <head>To all the godly, learned, and faithfull Paſtors of the ſeverall Churches in England, HENRY IACOB Miniſter of Gods word, <hi>wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth grace and peace to be multiplied in</hi> CHRIST IESVS.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>RETHREN, my hearts deſire &amp; prayer to God for the People of England is that they may be ſaved. And this you know well, can not be attained ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily with comfortable &amp; firme aſſurance in Gods Promiſes vnto vs, but by the due executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the whole &amp; entire Paſtorall office ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and ſet by Chriſt himſelf in his Churches to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. For which cauſe I have ben ſpecially at this time moved with inward compaſſion towards our whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; wherein through Gods mercifull goodnes the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell hath ben famouſly profeſſed now theſe 50. yeares al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt wholy togeather. And yet notwithſtanding never all this while have any of you (the Paſtors of our Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches) executed your whole and intiré function towardes your flockes. Being by all meanes forbidden and forcibly kept from one naturall part thereof, and moſt effectuall, which Chriſt in his word preſcribeth &amp; hath left for you and for all true Paſtors to performe. Namely the holy Governement and ſpiritual Diſcipline; as by the 2.4. &amp; 7. Reaſons in the firſt Aſſertion before hath appeared. Whence manifeſtly it is com to paſſe, that 3. vnſpeakeable evills do raigne among vs. Firſt a generall impeachment &amp; wracke of the ſoules health of the People every where
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:21672:45"/>throughout the Land, by wanting this Ordinarie meanes appointed of God for ſalvation to every man. Secondly, an iniurious ſpoyling of all you (beloved Brethren) the true and proper Paſtors in England of a principall part of your holy function and ſpirituall right. Third: no ſmall diminution of the honour of Chriſt and of his heavenly word.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Touching the firſt I do not ſay (as ſom ſeeme to do) that ſimply there is no ſalvation in our Chrches, nor true Chriſtianitie at all. But this I ſay, indeed Chriſt graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and apparantly doth impart ſalvation to many among vs; Howbeit that cometh not by our inioying the whole ordinarie meanes aſſigned of God for vs, which we haue not; but (as it were) by the one halfe thereof only, that is by the Preaching and Sacraments, which by his ſpeciall mercy we haue and do inioy. In which caſe whoſoever preſumeth of Gods loue, and aſſureth himſelfe of bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes with quiet contentment without longing for and ſeeking further to walke in the perfect way, now that it is diſcovered, peradventure he may deceaue himſelfe. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly many thouſands among vs do thus very common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make ſhipwrack. The rather ſeeing even that alſo which we haue ſound in our Land, is mixed and mingled with many other inventions and Traditions of men. And thoſe (though they ſay they are indifferent things, yet they) are not indifferently vſed, but neceſſarily vrged by authoritie &amp; impoſed vpon vs. Which ſurely are to none any helpes vnto life: but vnto many (if not to all) are dangerous ſnares vnto death. And this is all the good that comes by them.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond evill is the iniurious ſpoyling of all the true Paſtors in England of their moſt precious right, the Crowne of their Miniſtery, the ſpirituall governing and ordering of their owne flocks for whoſe ſoules they ſtand
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:21672:45"/>Bound to anſwer before God. O my Brethren, what are all your worldly benefites beſides to this loſſe? What are your dignities to this indignitie? Or elſe are you not the men you are taken to bee? Are you not rightly and truly Paſtors to your ſeverall flockes? Are you the Dioceſan Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Curates, and Subſtitutes only? Have you not pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly the charge of ſoules, and ſhall you anſwer to God nothing for the ſtraying &amp; leeſing of your ſheepe? If you thinke ſo, let the world vnderſtand this matter. If other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, looke to your charge, fulfill your miniſtery which you have receaved of the Lord. Or els conſider how you can be in ſuch an office, and yet not do the office; not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to do it. The things which God hath conioyned, who may ſeparate? The Lord for the ſaving of his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren needeth no mans ſinne, which you heere commit in thus violating his Ordinance. Yea he will ſave his by his owne meanes, and not as we thinke he will. Heaven and Earth may periſh, but one Iot or title of his ſpirituall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances may not periſh, nor be changed by men. It is not in men therfore nor Angels to diſpenſe with you heerein, nor to diſcharge you of a part of your holy office. Much leſſe may lay Chancelors or ſtrange Paſtors take into their hands the ſpirituall cenſures (which belong vnto you) both over your flockes and over your ſelves alſo. The laſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> but not the leaſt evill is, the manefeſt diminutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſts honour amongſt vs thereby. For whatſoever ſufficiency is yeelded vnto men to inſtitute and command theſe Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall ordinances, that is vniuſtly detracted from the proper and ſole perſon of Chriſt, and from his Word, as in the 1. &amp; 8. Reaſons before we ſhewed. Theſe things then are farr from indifferent matters or ſmall trifles in the Churches, as ſom fond men ſuggeſt, and ſtill reiterat. You
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:21672:46"/>do ſee in this Treatiſe (I hope) how directly contrary they are to Gods word, how preiudiciall and diſhonorable to your holy calling, &amp; likewiſe how pernicious to the ſoules of all the Chriſtians in the Land. Which alſo very expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience ſheweth vs too much. For how do Libertines and Atheiſts grow by this meanes? How doth Poperie and other Hereſies ſpread abroad &amp; gett footing by it? There is no other ſuch reaſon truly to be given of theſe evills, as this, even becauſe the Churches are deprived among vs (contrary to Chriſts ordinance) of their power to correct and redreſſe the ſame. And, becauſe every man wanteth this heavenly defenſe and preſervatiue appointed for vs of God; without which how ſhould they be preſerved? Yea it may be truly ſaid, that they all do want one part of their ordinary appointed and ſanctified food to eternall life, &amp; that they all do want the vſe of one of the Keyes which do open the Kingdom of heaven ordinarily, as before hath ben ſhewed. Why do you not therefore, bretheren, chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly now at this time, ſeeke vnto God by prayer and to our moſt wiſe and noble King, by humble and earneſt ſuit, both for your owne, for your peoples, yea for Chriſts due right? Our Soveraigne is a gracious Chriſtian Prince: He (as we dayly ſee) righteth every mans te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall wrongs who do come vnto him. Much more will he (being duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and diligently ſought vnto) give you &amp; your Flockes (every of which is Chriſts proper viſible Church) theſe ſo manifeſt and ſo neceſſarie ſpirituall rights appertayning vnto them, &amp; concerning ſo neerely all their ſoules health. And for Chriſts honor who wilbe more forward then he, who hath don many things moſt vertuouſly, moſt religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly already heeretofore. For the better procurement whereof now, and for the eaſier perſwading of you &amp; all
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:21672:46"/>men duely to ſeeke this bleſſing, I haue taken a little paines in the collecting of theſe Aſſertions and Reaſons before going. Hoping that even our Adverſaries heerein, who haue conſciences fearing God, and frameable by his word wiſhing ſincerely the right ſtate of Chriſts Viſible Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in England, will accord with vs, and not preferr their owne temporall reſpectes before Gods true glory, yea and their owne principall good. If any (as I feare to many) will reſiſt and pretend reaſon, and Religion, and care for the State, &amp;c. Them I deſire to be as willing, as we are, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianly to diſcuſſe theſe queſtions. Wherein humbly we deſire that the King him ſelfe would iudge; who is wiſe as an Angell of God, to vnderſtand &amp; determine this whole cauſe by the tryall and evidence of Gods written word. Which is and muſt be among Chriſtians the end of all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious controverſies. Wherefore now Brethren, I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend you to God and to the word of his grace, which is able to build vs further, &amp; to give vs an inheritance among them that are ſanctified.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Brother in the Lord <hi>HENRY IACOB.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <p>I am the way, the trueth, and the life.</p>
                  <bibl>Iohn 14.6.</bibl>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p>I will not give my glory to another.</p>
                  <bibl>Iſa. 42.8.</bibl>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <p>They teach things which they ought not for filthy lucres ſake.</p>
                  <bibl>Tit. 1.11.</bibl>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
